<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jesus Christ the great wonder discovered for the amazement of saints in a sermon preached before the right honorable the Lord Major of London and the honorable Court of Aldermen at Pauls / by Matthew Barker.</title>
            <author>Barker, Matthew, 1619-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30928</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B776</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23640</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07869655</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07869655</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40187</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30928)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40187)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1194:34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Jesus Christ the great wonder discovered for the amazement of saints in a sermon preached before the right honorable the Lord Major of London and the honorable Court of Aldermen at Pauls / by Matthew Barker.</title>
                  <author>Barker, Matthew, 1619-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.W. for Rapha Harford,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40187:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Jeſus Chriſt THE Great VVonder. DISCOVERED FOR THE Amazement of SAINTS. IN A SERMON Preached before the Right Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Lord Major of <hi>London,</hi> and the Honorable Court of <hi>Aldermen,</hi> at <hi>Pauls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By MATTHEW BARKER, Preacher of the Goſpel at <hi>Leonards Eaſt-Cheap. LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>O the depth of the Riches both of the wiſdom and knowledge of God! how unſearchable are his judgements, and his wayes paſt finding out!</hi> 
               <bibl>Rom. 11. 33.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Quando mens ſe ad deum cum am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re integrè convertit, incomprehenſibili luce in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ejus effulgente, rationis &amp; intellectus oculus, reverberatus caligat.</hi> 
               <bibl>Iſagog. Corderii ad myſt. Theol cap. 7.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <bibl>
                  <hi>Dionyſ. Areop. de divin. nomin. Cap.</hi> 7.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. W.</hi> for <hi>Rapha Harford,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>States-Arms</hi> in <hi>Little Brittain.</hi> 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40187:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40187:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, Thomas Andrews, LORD MAIOR, AND The HONORABLE COURT of ALDERMEN.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou were pleaſed to <hi>Order</hi> this Sermon to the <hi>Preſs;</hi> but I hope it hath already had <hi>one Impreſsion</hi> upon your hearts, and I intended it for no other, and is the moſt noble and excellent kind of Printing; when the heart comes to be
<pb facs="tcp:40187:3"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as a Book ingraven with the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravings of God,</hi> &amp; <hi>the Epiſtle of Jeſus Chriſt, written not with ink, but the Spirit of the living God.</hi> What I before<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3. 3.</note> preſented to your ears, I now again preſent to your eyes (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) and if by either or both it ſhall reach your hearts, I have my reward; You ſhould have had it ſooner, but ſome troubles in my ſpirit, and ſome affairs in my hand have retarded it: But now you have it, and neither in matter or form much different from what it was. And the bleſsing of heaven attend it, that it may either make or renew ſome heavenly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsions upon your ſouls; for though it is true what the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom. 10. That Faith cometh by hearing,</hi> yet it is alſo as true what the Church ſaith, <hi>Lam. 3. 51. Mine eye affecteth my heart.</hi> Then are the ſenſes of the body in their higheſt and propereſt operations, when they let in
<pb facs="tcp:40187:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> upon the ſoul thoſe <hi>Idea's</hi> which will indeed raiſe, refreſh, and nouriſh it.</p>
            <p>My great <hi>plot</hi> was, in this Diſcourſe, (pardon this <hi>plot)</hi> to make you all <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives;</hi> not to my ſelf, but to TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH and JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST; and I knew not how to do it by a more probable <hi>ſtratagem,</hi> then to ſet up this Jeſus in his WONDERF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LNES before you, as conceiving, that to men truly <hi>ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> he cannot be preſented under a more powerful and perſwaſive Notion. And ſo I thought it might be very ſutable to men in Power and place; for the heart that is moſt effectually caught and captivated of Jeſus Chriſt, is beſt <hi>accompliſht</hi> for the ſincere and vigorous proſecution of publique affairs: Never doth the ſoul move aright in any ſervice, if it be not <hi>originally</hi> drawn of him, and <hi>ultimately</hi> carried forth unto him. And O that your choiſeſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections
<pb facs="tcp:40187:4"/> might centre in his <hi>perſon,</hi> and your chiefeſt endeavours in his <hi>glory:</hi> We read in <hi>Rev. 19. 1.</hi> of <hi>a great voyce of much people in heaven, ſaying, Allelujah, ſalvation and glory, and honour, and power to the Lord our God.</hi> What ſalvation, what glory, what honour, and power the Lord hath given to his people in theſe dayes, he expects they ſhould give them back again to him; that as they are his by their coming from him, ſo they may again be made his by returning them back unto him; and then ſhall we approve our ſelves to be of thoſe <hi>people in heaven. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles</hi> when he had drawn ſome curious piece, would ſet it in publique view, and place himſelf behind the curtain to hearken what would be ſaid of it by the people paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by: Jeſus Chriſt hath ſet before us in his great works among us a fair <hi>draught,</hi> a <hi>lively repreſentation</hi> of his glorious
<pb facs="tcp:40187:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> power, wiſdom, juſtice, and mercy; and doth he not now ſtand ſtill, and liſten what the hearts, tongues, and actings of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſpeak concerning it?</p>
            <p>Our great tranſactions were lately in our <hi>VVars</hi> abroad; they are now likely to be in our <hi>Counſels</hi> at home: Much of <hi>God</hi> hath been ſeen in thoſe; and O that nothing of <hi>ſelf</hi> might be ſeen in theſe: I hope at laſt God will direct us to find out one <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Centre</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> wherein all honeſt hearts will meet.</p>
            <p>The Lord give your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> and all others that ſit with you at the <hi>Stern</hi> of this City, wiſdom to ſayl between the two rocks of <hi>ANARCHY</hi> and <hi>TYRANNY,</hi> and then I hope you will arrive ſafe at the much longed for <hi>Haven</hi> of common righteouſneſs, and peace. It is not for me to preſcribe any thing in this nature. Only I ſhall pray, that the two Staves of <hi>BANDS</hi> and <hi>BEAUTY,</hi> may
<pb facs="tcp:40187:5"/> alwayes ſtand at the gates of this <hi>City,</hi> by our ſweet enjoyment of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in his Ordinances, and of <hi>one another</hi> in unity and love.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>firſt</hi> degree of happineſs would be, not to differ; but the <hi>ſecond</hi> is, to mannage our differences with humility and wiſdom, and to take them up before they prove like a <hi>breach of the Sea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ought to <hi>mark thoſe that cauſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions,</hi> much more thoſe that delight in them. I ſhall no longer detain you from the peruſal of thoſe poor and broken meditations that follow; though they came from me in weakneſs, yet I hope, they will riſe up in you with power, which will be a <hi>CROWN</hi> of Glory, and rejoycing to him, who deſires to his utmoſt to be ſerviceable to the great <hi>Intereſt</hi> of your ſpiritual Eſtate,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Matthew Barker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40187:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Iſaiah Chap. 9. part of the 6. ver.</bibl>
               <q>And his name ſhall be called Wonderful, &amp;c.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F all the <hi>Prophets,</hi> this <hi>Prophet Iſaiah</hi> is the moſt <hi>Evangelical:</hi> what <hi>Paul</hi> was among the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> that is <hi>Iſaiah</hi> among the <hi>Prophets</hi> in the <hi>Old:</hi> as the One had the higheſt <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> the Other had the cleareſt <hi>Viſion;</hi> of which you read <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 6. and is expreſly ſaid to be of <hi>Chriſt in his glory,</hi> John 12. 41. ſpeaking more diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his birth, natures, life, ſufferings, death, his kingdom and glorious adminiſtrations in the world, then the reſt of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Qui Iſaiam legerit, verſari ſe putet in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelio.</hi> Hier.</note> ſo that he is oftener quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> then all the reſt of the <hi>Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the beginning of this Chapter, he ſpeaks <hi>pure Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel:</hi> having in the preceding Chapters been foretelling and threatning a <hi>gloomy</hi> night of <hi>Captivity</hi> and <hi>deſolation</hi> coming upon <hi>Iudah and Ieruſalem,</hi> as you read <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. 17, 18. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. 7, 8. in this Chapter to keep their <hi>heads</hi> above water, that they might not <hi>ſink</hi> under the <hi>fear</hi> or <hi>feeling</hi> of thoſe <hi>heavy</hi> afflictions, doth preſent to their thoughts the near approach of the <hi>Meſsiah,</hi> and that glorious <hi>reſtitution, ſalvation</hi> and <hi>deliverance</hi> which come along with him, upon the <hi>world;</hi> that they might
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40187:6"/> be able to look through the <hi>darkneſs</hi> of the night, to the <hi>beauty</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> of <hi>that day</hi> that was <hi>erſt-while</hi> to ſhine forth upon the Earth: And this day is <hi>repreſented</hi> by the <hi>day</hi> of their <hi>deliverance</hi> from the <hi>Babyloniſh Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> as the <hi>ſhadow</hi> of it, in the beginning of this <hi>Chapter,</hi> that their joy might be the more <hi>enlarged,</hi> and this <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance</hi> more welcome, when they ſhould receive it, not alone as a temporal <hi>deliverance,</hi> but as a <hi>type</hi> and <hi>pledge</hi> of that ſpiritual <hi>ſalvation</hi> which the Lord Jeſus was to <hi>adminiſter</hi> at his coming.</p>
            <p>This day of Chriſt is preſented by the <hi>Prophet, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching,</hi> in this Chapter, with theſe ſeveral <hi>goodly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Light.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ioy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Victory.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt is <hi>Light:</hi> as in ver. 2. <hi>The people that walked in darkneſs, have ſeen a great light:</hi> All light, hath <hi>its</hi> pleaſure; the <hi>loweſt</hi> light, that which is <hi>ſenſible</hi> and <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible,</hi> is pleaſant, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11. 7. but the <hi>higher</hi> the light is, the more <hi>ſutable</hi> to man, and ſo <hi>the more</hi> pleaſant: This light that ſhines from Chriſt, is <hi>intellectual, ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,</hi> breaking out from the <hi>higheſt ſphear,</hi> and the <hi>firſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> of light.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Second is <hi>Ioy:</hi> as in ver. 3. <hi>They joy before thee;</hi> Which is <hi>expreſt</hi> by two of the <hi>higheſt</hi> joys in <hi>nature;</hi> the one is of <hi>harveſt,</hi> when the Husbandman <hi>reaps</hi> the fruit of his <hi>long</hi> toyl and travels: The other is, of <hi>divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> the ſpoils; when after the enemy is <hi>routed,</hi> the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>won,</hi> the danger and difficulty of the ſervice over, the <hi>Soldiour</hi> makes his <hi>triumph,</hi> and divides <hi>the ſpoil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:40187:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>3. Third is <hi>Victory:</hi> which you read in ver. 4. which is deſcribed in the</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Parts</hi> of it.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Manner</hi> of it.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Author</hi> of it.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The ſeveral parts of it, ver. 4. <hi>Thou haſt broken the yoke of his burthen, and the ſtaffe of his ſhoulder, the rod of his oppreſſor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>The yoke of his burthen,</hi> or burthenſom <hi>yoke,</hi> which is the <hi>Law,</hi> which Chriſt hath <hi>broken</hi> off from the <hi>necks</hi> of Saints.</p>
            <p>Second is, <hi>The ſtaffe of his ſhoulder,</hi> which is the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and guilt of ſin, wherewith the Conſcience is <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted,</hi> and beaten, and the <hi>ſpirit</hi> in man <hi>enſlaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Third is, <hi>The rod,</hi> or the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Scepter of his oppreſſor,</hi> which is the dominion and <hi>reign</hi> of the <hi>devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Next we have the <hi>manner</hi> of it, expreſſed by a two-fold <hi>parallel:</hi> Firſt is, that Victory of <hi>Gideon</hi> over the <hi>Midianites: As in the day of Midian,</hi> ver. 4. recorded <hi>Judg.</hi> 7. and an eminent <hi>type</hi> of this: Firſt, in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour <hi>Gideon</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a <hi>Exſcidit.</hi>
               </note>, which ſignifies one that doth <hi>cut off,</hi> or deſtroy; as he did, cut off the enemies of Iſrael, and bring in their <hi>deliverance;</hi> ſo doth Jeſus Chriſt for his people.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in the perſon <hi>Conquered,</hi> the <hi>Midianites;</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cauſam egi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Midian</hi> ſignifies <hi>Contention,</hi> or <hi>pleading in Judgement</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another: This <hi>Midian CHRIST</hi> doth <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw</hi> and ſilence: whatever <hi>Sin,</hi> the <hi>Law, Satan,</hi> or <hi>Conſcience</hi> could plead againſt us; Chriſt hath <hi>put to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> and overcome, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> aſſerts by a <hi>word</hi> very
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40187:7"/> ſignificant to this purpoſe, Rom. 8. 33. <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or who ſhall call them into judgement?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in the aſſiſtance <hi>he uſed</hi> in the Conqueſt; which was from <hi>Abiezer,</hi> ſignifying <hi>the help of my father:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 6. 34.</note> ſo Chriſt prevailed in the <hi>power</hi> and <hi>aſsiſtance</hi> of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, in the <hi>paucity</hi> of his men, whereby he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered; his Army of <hi>thirty two thouſand,</hi> being reduced to <hi>three hundred:</hi> none of thoſe that were fearfull, or <hi>bowed down upon their knees</hi> to drink, <hi>engaging</hi> with him in the battle: So fares it with Jeſus Chriſt in thoſe <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual battles</hi> he is fighting in the world: ſome <hi>deſponding</hi> by carnal fear, others <hi>bowed down</hi> by earthly <hi>engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and <hi>intereſts,</hi> do baſely fall off, going back to <hi>ſelf,</hi> and the world.</p>
            <p>But laſtly, and eſpecially in the <hi>ſtrangeneſs</hi> of it: <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon</hi> prevailed not by <hi>might</hi> nor <hi>ſtrength;</hi> not by wont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>policy,</hi> or warlike <hi>ſtratagems,</hi> but by <hi>Lamps</hi> and <hi>Pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and the <hi>ſound of Trumpets:</hi> So <hi>our Lord Ieſus</hi> by <hi>Lamps</hi> and <hi>Pitchers,</hi> by the light of <hi>Truth</hi> in <hi>Earthen veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,</hi> and by the <hi>ſounding</hi> of the Goſpel, doth deſtroy the <hi>powers</hi> of darkneſs, the Kingdom of <hi>Sathan,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founds and ſcatters all the enemies of our ſalvation.</p>
            <p>This is the firſt Parallel.</p>
            <p>Next, it is <hi>paralleld</hi> with other ordinary battles and victories, ver. 5. <hi>Every battle of the Warriour is with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed noiſe, and with garments rolled in blood, but this ſhall be</hi> (or as we may better read it) <hi>and it is,</hi> or <hi>will be with burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>the fuel of fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So in Chriſts <hi>ſpiritual</hi> battles, you have all theſe <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitants:</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:40187:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> here is a <hi>confuſed noiſe,</hi> when he comes and ſets up his <hi>ſtandard</hi> within us, and is <hi>ſubduing us</hi> to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; how do <hi>carnal reaſon,</hi> the <hi>wiſdom</hi> and luſts of the fleſh, make a <hi>noiſe</hi> within us, <hi>contradicting</hi> and oppoſing Chriſt in his word, works, and wayes within us: Two <hi>irreconcileable</hi> parties claſhing and fighting againſt each other, do bring forth this <hi>confuſed noiſe,</hi> and tumult in the ſoul.</p>
            <p>And <hi>in other</hi> victories we may ſee <hi>garments rolled in blood;</hi> ſo neither is this <hi>ſpiritual</hi> victory without <hi>blood;</hi> Chriſt overcame by his <hi>blood;</hi> ſo do Saints overcome, by <hi>the blood of the Lamb:</hi> and <hi>their garments are made white,</hi> being <hi>dipped</hi> and <hi>rolled</hi> in this <hi>blood.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 7. 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, other victories are attended with <hi>burnings;</hi> firing of Gates, Houſes, Cities, and other <hi>fuel</hi> of fire: So this ſpiritual battle and <hi>victory</hi> is not without <hi>fire:</hi> the <hi>fire</hi> of the Spirit is <hi>burning</hi> within us, whatever is <hi>fleſhly</hi> and <hi>carnal;</hi> whatever is <hi>hay and ſtubble,</hi> is the <hi>fuel</hi> of this <hi>fire:</hi> and the <hi>day of the Lord,</hi> when he comes to conquer, will <hi>conſume</hi> and devour it.</p>
            <p>Thus we have ſeen <hi>this Victory</hi> in the <hi>manner</hi> of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, it is ſet forth in the <hi>Author</hi> of it: who is now <hi>the warriour</hi> that fights theſe battles, the <hi>Conqueror</hi> that ſubdues theſe enemies: here are great <hi>Victories at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieved,</hi> brave <hi>exploits</hi> acted, ſtrong and puiſſant <hi>adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries</hi> broken: do you not long to ſee the perſon brought forth in view, whoſe <hi>atchievements</hi> ye have heard the high <hi>reports</hi> of, and before you ſee him, are ſpeaking within your ſelves, as they in the Goſpel, <hi>What manner of man is this!</hi> Lo, the verſe I have read preſents him to you: It is no other then a <hi>Child<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For unto us a Child is born, and unto us a Son is given, &amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Child</hi> is the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40187:8"/> ſame which was ſpoken of <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. 14. that was to be born of a Virgin, and whoſe name is called <hi>Immanuel:</hi> The ſame with that child born of the Propheteſs, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Maher-Shalal-haſh baz,</hi> not <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> as the Jews would fain underſtand the Text, but our Lord Jeſus himſelf: who is preſented in this 6. verſe under ſuch a deſcription as cannot agree to any creature.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He is deſcribed in his <hi>twofold nature, a child born, a ſon given:</hi> the <hi>child</hi> of the Virgin in reſpect of his <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity,</hi> the Son of God in reſpect of his <hi>Divinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. In his <hi>Dedication</hi> to his people in both natures; he is <hi>a child born to us, a ſon given to us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. In the <hi>ſoveraign</hi> power and <hi>authority</hi> wherewith he is inveſted; <hi>The government ſhall be upon his ſhoulder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. In the <hi>names</hi> wherewith he is <hi>ſtyled,</hi> which are theſe five: Firſt is <hi>Wonderful:</hi> The ſecond <hi>Counſellor:</hi> The third the <hi>Mighty God:</hi> The fourth the <hi>Everlaſting Father,</hi> or the <hi>Father of Eternity:</hi> The laſt the <hi>Prince of Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bernard</hi> applies theſe names thus, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Admirabilis nativitate, Conſiliarius praedicatione, fortis Deus in operatione, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeculi in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectione, Princeps pacis in perpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uâ be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atitudine.</hi> Ber. Serm. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Wonderful, in his birth: Counſellor in his Doctrine: The Mighty God in his working: Father of Eternity in his reſurrection: Prince of Peace in our eternal happineſs.</hi> Others conceive theſe names relate to the ſeveral parts of mans <hi>ſalvation:</hi> Firſt, <hi>Wonderful, in the new birth,</hi> ſo ſtrangely changing the courſe of <hi>corrupt</hi> nature. Secondly, <hi>Counſellor,</hi> in making man wiſe in his choiſe, and to <hi>diſcern</hi> of things that differ. Thirdly, <hi>A ſtrong God,</hi> in throwing down the ſtrong holds of ſin. Fourthly, <hi>Father of Eternity,</hi> by infuſing an <hi>Everlaſting life.</hi> Laſtly, <hi>Prince of Peace,</hi> in reconciling us to the <hi>Father,</hi> and quieting and ſatisfying the <hi>ſoul</hi> of man.</p>
            <p>There is nothing in the verſe but what is of <hi>ſingular</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:40187:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> concernment; every word hath its diſtinct <hi>Emphaſis:</hi> each of theſe names hath a <hi>treaſure</hi> of truth within it: but I have <hi>ſingled</hi> out the firſt of the names by which he is ſet forth, to ſpend my preſent ſtrength and time upon, <hi>viz.</hi> his name <hi>Wonderful:</hi> And that which invited my thoughts to this <hi>ſubject</hi> in this place, was, becauſe Chriſt hath made himſelf <hi>eminently</hi> known by this name in our dayes, and we are caſt upon thoſe Ages of the world wherein he will yet further merit and <hi>magnifie</hi> it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wonderful.</hi> The word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which<note place="margin">Vid. Avenar. Lex.</note> ſignifies, to be vailed or hidden from the eyes and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding</hi> of men; becauſe things <hi>wonderful</hi> are things that lie hid, whoſe <hi>depth</hi> cannot be ſounded, nor cauſe diſcovered: This name applied to Chriſt, ſignifies, as <hi>A Lapide</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Rerum mirabilium the ſauros inaeſtimabiles in Chriſto eſſe abſconditos,</hi> that the ineſtimable treaſures of wonderful things are hidden in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Simmachus</hi> tranſlates the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a <hi>Paradox,</hi> or <hi>Paradoxnes</hi> it ſelf: and indeed he is not ſo much <hi>admirable</hi> as <hi>admirability:</hi> Among all thoſe <hi>pompous titles</hi> which the Princes of the earth have aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, none ever have aſſumed this, it being reſerved as <hi>peculiar</hi> to Jeſus Chriſt: Some conceive that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet here alludes to the <hi>Angel</hi> that converſed with <hi>Manoah, Judg.</hi> 13. 18. who being asked his name, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, his name was <hi>Peli,</hi> or <hi>Wonderful.</hi> And <hi>Jacob</hi> asked the Angel his name he contended with, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32. He anſwers, <hi>Wherefore doſt thou ask my name?</hi> In denying to tell him it, he doth in a manner confeſs it, that it is <hi>wonderful. Moſes</hi> asked the ſame thing of God, to know his Name; He anſwers him, <hi>I am that I am;</hi> As if he<note place="margin">Exod. 3. 13.</note> ſhould ſay, no name can fully expreſs me; but <hi>what I am that I am;</hi> His Eſſence is ſo <hi>wonderful,</hi> that no name,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40187:9"/> unleſs it be the name <hi>Wonderful,</hi> can well agree to him. The firſt uſe of names was to deſcribe the <hi>nature</hi> of things; but the nature of God being every way <hi>incomprehenſible,</hi> it cannot be poſſibly confined within the limit of any <hi>name;</hi> or if it could, yet that <hi>name</hi> neither man, nor An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels could <hi>comprehend;</hi> and therefore the Jews eſteemed the name Jehovah <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an unſpeakable <hi>name: Divines</hi> ſay that no <hi>definition</hi> can be given of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Being is <hi>tranſcendent;</hi> infinitely differing from all things <hi>viſible</hi> or <hi>conceiveable;</hi> And therefore in the moſt comprehenſive <hi>definition, ſemper maneret aliquid extra,</hi> ſomething which it could not poſſibly reach; And ſo we may ſay alſo, that no name can <hi>poſitively</hi> and fully expreſs the <hi>tranſcendent</hi> excellency of his Being, but it muſt needs fall infinitely ſhort of comprehending him.</p>
            <p>So that one of the <hi>Ancients</hi> ſpeaking of God, ſaith, That he is both <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; without name, and yet of many names, becauſe by whatever <hi>name</hi> we call any <hi>excellency</hi> or good in the creature, it may <hi>emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently</hi> be praedicated of him; for he is both <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, all things that the <hi>Creature</hi> is, and yet nothing that the <hi>Creature</hi> is; all things may be both <hi>affirmed</hi> and <hi>denied</hi> of him; for ſeeing he is infinitely above all that <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency</hi> that is in the creature, therefore as much above every name whereby that <hi>excellency</hi> is called:</p>
            <p>As when he is called <hi>life, light, beauty, ſweetneſs,</hi> yet he is none of theſe things as they are in the <hi>creature,</hi> or <hi>apprehended</hi> by us, but in ſuch a <hi>tranſcendent</hi> way as is <hi>unconceiveable</hi> to all created underſtanding. He is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as one <hi>elegantly</hi> ſpeaks.</p>
            <p>Some names attributed to God ſpeak him forth in his <hi>abſolute Eſſence</hi> and Being, as <hi>Jehovah, El-ſhaddai;</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:40187:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Others in his eſſential properties, as <hi>Almighty, Juſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Zanch. de naturâ dei lib. 1. cap.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>True, God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others in his relation to his <hi>creatures,</hi> as <hi>Lord, King, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others in thoſe <hi>effects</hi> that he brings forth upon them; as when he puts forth his Eſſence in a way of <hi>il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumination</hi> we call him <hi>light,</hi> of <hi>quickning</hi> we call him <hi>life,</hi> of <hi>ſupporting</hi> we call him a <hi>rock;</hi> of <hi>defence,</hi> we call him a <hi>refuge,</hi> or <hi>high Tower:</hi> though theſe <hi>operations</hi> of God deſcend upon us, yet his <hi>Eſſence</hi> (as one ſpeaks) abides <hi>inviſible;</hi> God in favor to us, and condeſcent to our underſtanding, expreſſeth himſelf by theſe names, that we might be able a little to <hi>apprehend</hi> him.</p>
            <p>But there is no name that doth ſo fully expreſs him in the <hi>incomprehenſibleneſs,</hi> and <hi>infiniteneſs</hi> of his Being as the name <hi>Wonderful.</hi> In his other names we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of him under ſome finite <hi>notion;</hi> but this name <hi>Wonderful</hi> ſpeaks him forth as one that <hi>ſurpaſſeth</hi> all the knowledge of the creature, the <hi>flight</hi> of mans higheſt thoughts: for that which is within the compaſs of his <hi>reaſon,</hi> that he never wonders at; but when he meets with ſome thing that <hi>tranſcends</hi> his reach, that ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows up his <hi>underſtanding,</hi> that he calls <hi>Wonderful,</hi> and ſtands <hi>amazed</hi> at; therefore the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> ſay, that the proper object of admiration is <hi>res incognita,</hi> a thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known and undiſcerned; and therefore <hi>God</hi> cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be ſaid to <hi>wonder,</hi> to whom nothing lies hid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Divines</hi> diſtinguiſh between <hi>Mirandum &amp; Miraculum.</hi> That is <hi>wonderful</hi> which is <hi>unuſual</hi> or unknown, proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from ſome <hi>unwonted</hi> or <hi>und ſcovered</hi> cauſe in <hi>Nature:</hi> That is a <hi>miracle</hi> which is above <hi>Nature,</hi> tranſcends the utmoſt power and compaſs of <hi>Nature,</hi> in which we ſee the <hi>Godhead</hi> putting forth it ſelf in its <hi>abſtracted</hi> and immediate vigor. Now both theſe may be ſeen emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40187:10"/> in Jeſus Chriſt; here are <hi>wonders,</hi> here are <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles,</hi> here are <hi>myſteries,</hi> and all the <hi>deep things</hi> of God are <hi>treaſured</hi> up in him, and <hi>ſhine forth</hi> from him upon the world.</p>
            <p>Before we look upon him <hi>directly</hi> in this name of his, and the reaſons of it, we ſhall preſent him under ſome of thoſe <hi>types</hi> and <hi>ſhadows,</hi> whereby he was <hi>repreſented</hi> before his actual <hi>coming</hi> into the world.</p>
            <p>We find him typed forth by <hi>wonderful</hi> perſons, and <hi>wonderful</hi> things under the Law, and yet himſelf more <hi>wonderful</hi> then all.</p>
            <p>For Perſons.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Adam,</hi> a <hi>wonderful</hi> perſon, formed by the <hi>immediate</hi> hand of God without the concurrence of thoſe <hi>natural</hi> cauſes by which men are <hi>ordinarily</hi> brought forth; ſo was <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adam</hi> had all knowledge, both of God, and the creature by immediate <hi>illumination,</hi> and <hi>infuſion;</hi> ſo had Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adam</hi> had <hi>mankind</hi> in his loyns, a world within him ſo had Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adam</hi> had an univerſal <hi>Lordſhip</hi> and <hi>ſuperintendency</hi> over the whole Creation; ſo had <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So alſo <hi>Noah,</hi> a <hi>wonderful</hi> perſon; a <hi>man</hi> that lived in <hi>two worlds,</hi> was the term or <hi>period</hi> of the <hi>Old world,</hi> as it is called 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 5. and was the beginning and <hi>founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the New world after the Flood, which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired and <hi>built up again by him,</hi> as you read, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. Even ſo Jeſus Chriſt lived firſt in the <hi>old</hi> natural ſtate of man, being under the <hi>Law;</hi> as the old man, or <hi>Adam</hi> is, and was the end or period of that; and then raiſed up
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40187:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> and founded the new <hi>ſpiritual world,</hi> making the <hi>old ſtate</hi> of things to paſs away upon his <hi>Croſs,</hi> and bringing all things into a <hi>new ſtate</hi> at his Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>The next <hi>wonderful man</hi> we ſhall ſpeak of, is <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedek,</hi> whom the Apoſtle gives a <hi>ſtrange</hi> deſcription of, <hi>Heb. 7. Without father, without mother, without begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or end of days, and abiding a Prieſt continually.</hi> Some conceived him to be <hi>Sem</hi> the ſon of <hi>Noah,</hi> as the <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. Cunaeum lib. 2. cap. 3. expreſsè.</note> and <hi>Hebrews:</hi> Others an <hi>Angel,</hi> as <hi>Origen.</hi> Others the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> or a certain <hi>divine power</hi> of God greater then Chriſt, as the <hi>Melchiſedecians.</hi> Others Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf appearing in <hi>humane form,</hi> as <hi>Cunaeus,</hi> and others. And ſome conceive him one of the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Canaan,</hi> as <hi>A Lapide,</hi> whom you may read upon the place: who ever he was, he was a <hi>wonderful</hi> perſon: Said to be <hi>without father or mother;</hi> meant, either becauſe his <hi>Genealogy</hi> is not ſpoken of; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: or in reference to his <hi>Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> not deſcending upon him by Father, Mother, or any <hi>natural</hi> ſucceſſion, as it did upon the <hi>Levitical Prieſts,</hi> which is the more probable.</p>
            <p>Said alſo to be <hi>without beginning or end of days. viz.</hi> as a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> his <hi>Prieſthood</hi> not being after the <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Aaron,</hi> which was to expire, but veſted in him upon ſuch an <hi>account</hi> as was eminently to be held up, <hi>eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,</hi> and <hi>perpetuated</hi> in the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And to this man <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the <hi>Levitical Prieſthood</hi> in his loyns that was to receive <hi>Tithes,</hi> pays <hi>Tithes</hi> of all. A <hi>wonderful</hi> perſon indeed; and yet in all this but a ſhadow of him that is far more <hi>wonderful;</hi> Jeſus Chriſt: who is indeed <hi>without Father and mother, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out beginning and end of days, and abideth a Prieſt for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver:</hi> to whom we all ſpiritually are to pay <hi>tithes,</hi> by acknowledging that we <hi>hold</hi> all of him, and by <hi>reſigning</hi> all back again unto him.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:40187:11"/>
            <p>Another <hi>wonderful</hi> man was <hi>Iſaac,</hi> iſſuing out of the <hi>dry,</hi> and as it were, <hi>dead</hi> bodies of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sarah;</hi> when the vigor and vertue of <hi>nature</hi> was even expired; that <hi>Sarah laughed</hi> at the Promiſe, ſaying, <hi>How can this be?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſprings as a <hi>root out of a dry ground,</hi> as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53. 2. When his <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Kingdom</hi> riſeth in the world, it is uſually out of cauſes that ſeem <hi>barren</hi> and <hi>improbable;</hi> and when he riſeth, and grows up within us, it is out of a <hi>dry</hi> and <hi>barren</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, making the Wilderneſs to bud and bloſſom as the Roſe, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 35. 1.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Iſaac</hi> one in whom all Nations were to be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; which is only true of Jeſus Chriſt, in <hi>whom</hi> we <hi>are bleſſed with all bleſsings in heavenly things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo <hi>Joſeph,</hi> another <hi>perſon</hi> to be wondered at, fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with heavenly <hi>wiſdom</hi> to interpret ſecrets, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the <hi>hidden things</hi> of darkneſs, and therefore was called <hi>Zaphnath Paaneah, Gen.</hi> 41. 45. But Chriſt in this reſpect more <hi>wonderful,</hi> declaring the deep Counſels of God, and opening the <hi>Treaſuries</hi> of the <hi>higheſt wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> to the world.</p>
            <p>Again, a <hi>wonderful</hi> perſon, ſaving all <hi>Egypt</hi> alive in the midſt of <hi>famine;</hi> and his <hi>father</hi> and <hi>brethren</hi> from death by that <hi>proviſion</hi> which he ſtored up, and diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to them; ſo Jeſus Chriſt hath all heavenly <hi>provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> ſtored up in himſelf, whereby he doth feed and nouriſh the ſouls of men in the midſt of that <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual famine</hi> that ſin hath brought upon them.</p>
            <p>And yet again <hi>wonderful;</hi> to whom his <hi>Brethrens ſheafes, and the Sun, Moon, and eleven Stars did obeiſance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 37. 7, 9.</note> in a Dream or Viſion: So <hi>all power in Heaven and Earth</hi> is in the hand of Chriſt; and to him <hi>every knee ſhall bow.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:40187:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>To mention but one perſon more of many: <hi>Sampſon</hi> a<note place="margin">Judg. 14, 16.</note> 
               <hi>wonderful</hi> man; who <hi>ſlew a Lion with his hand, and tare him in pieces like a Kid:</hi> So doth Jeſus Chriſt ſlay and conquer <hi>Satan,</hi> break his power and kingdom in pieces.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Sampſon</hi> with the <hi>jawbone of an Aſs,</hi> a ſimple creature, ſlew above a <hi>thouſand</hi> men: So Chriſt by the <hi>Word of his mouth,</hi> which the world accounts <hi>fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> ſlays the wicked with a <hi>deſtructive,</hi> and his people with a <hi>wholſom</hi> and <hi>ſaving</hi> ſlaughter.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Sampſon</hi> took the gates of the City <hi>Gaza;</hi> and <hi>carries them away with the bars and poſts thereof:</hi> So our <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> carries away the <hi>gates and bars of death and ſin.</hi> And ſo the <hi>withs,</hi> and <hi>green cords</hi> wherewith he was bound, he brake them in pieces like Tow: Even ſo Jeſus Chriſt breaks aſunder thoſe bands of the <hi>Law,</hi> and ſin that were upon him; delivered <hi>himſelf</hi> from them, and his <hi>people</hi> by his preſence in them. We might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in <hi>Moſes, Ioſhua, David,</hi> and many others, of whom ſuch <hi>wonderful</hi> things are reported: but time would fail.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the <hi>wonderful</hi> perſons.</p>
            <p>We ſhall next ſet before you ſome <hi>Wonderful</hi> things, that have been from the <hi>beginning</hi> of the world, which were all as <hi>ſhadows</hi> to repreſent, and <hi>harbingers</hi> to uſher in this <hi>perſon</hi> in the Text, whoſe name is <hi>Wonderful,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world. To ſpeak briefly,</p>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>Tree of life</hi> in Paradiſe, a <hi>ſtrange</hi> thing, that the man that eat thereof ſhould live for ever: This <hi>tree of life</hi> is Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And ſo <hi>Jacobs Ladder,</hi> though ſeen but in a <hi>viſion,</hi> yet was <hi>wonderful</hi> to <hi>Iacob,</hi> whoſe <hi>bottom was upon the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40187:12"/> Earth, and the top reached Heaven:</hi> Jeſus Chriſt is this <hi>Ladder,</hi> uniting God and Man, Heaven and Earth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>Alſo the <hi>burning buſh</hi> that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw, a ſtrange thing:<note place="margin">Exod. 3. 3.</note> 
               <hi>a great ſight,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> called it, for a <hi>little</hi> buſh, and a <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring</hi> flame to meet together, and yet the buſh not conſumed of it: So in Jeſus Chriſt, for the <hi>brightneſs</hi> and glory of the <hi>divinity</hi> to dwel and ſhine forth in the <hi>humanity,</hi> and the humanity not to be <hi>extinguiſht</hi> or <hi>overwhelmed</hi> by it, is very <hi>wonderful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark, a ſtrange thing: That being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Rudder, Anchor, Ballaſt, &amp;c.</hi> ſhould yet preſerve <hi>Noah,</hi> his houſe, and all the creatures with him upon the <hi>raging</hi> waters for an hundred and fifty dayes: So<note place="margin">Gen. 7. 24.</note> Jeſus Chriſt in a more <hi>wonderful</hi> manner doth preſerve his people from that <hi>deluge</hi> of divine wrath wherewith others are overwhelmed.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Moſes rod</hi> turned into a Serpent, devoured the <hi>Serpents</hi> of the <hi>Egyptians:</hi> a very ſtrange thing. So Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt that <hi>brazen Serpent,</hi> in the likeneſs of <hi>ſerpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, ſinful fleſh,</hi> doth devour the <hi>Serpent</hi> of ſin, and the fleſh within us.</p>
            <p>So alſo the <hi>red Sea</hi> divided, a <hi>wonderful</hi> thing: To ſee a vaſt raging Sea to <hi>divide</hi> it ſelf, being at the place of its <hi>diviſion</hi> at leaſt 36. Engliſh miles over: and the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to ſtand as a <hi>ſolid wall</hi> on each ſide: and ſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue for ſeveral dayes together, as is <hi>probable,</hi> that ſo many thouſand Iſraelites, with their wives and children, with their beaſts and cattel might paſs over: whereas nothing is ſo <hi>fluid,</hi> and more hardly <hi>contained</hi> within its <hi>bounds,</hi> as water is.</p>
            <p>And then for the waters to move, and take their courſe upon the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> that not one of them was
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40187:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſaved: and to keep ſtill <hi>divided</hi> for the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to paſs over, that not one of them was drowned, and that at one and the ſame time alſo, as may be conceived, is not this <hi>wonderful?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet this <hi>great wonder</hi> is but the <hi>ſhadow</hi> of a far greater in our Lord Jeſus: He is this <hi>red Sea,</hi> into whoſe death, and grave believers <hi>ſpiritually</hi> enter, by <hi>dying</hi> to ſin, and <hi>retiring</hi> from the world, and by this (as the Iſraelites) they paſs into life, ſalvation, victory, and the Reſt of God: leaving the luſts of the fleſh, as the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them, to be both <hi>covered,</hi> and <hi>deſtroyed</hi> for ever.</p>
            <p>And ſo <hi>water out of the rock,</hi> a wondrous thing, for a dry <hi>rock</hi> to give forth water: and this water <hi>to go along</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 4.</note> 
               <hi>with the people</hi> (as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaks) and adminiſter <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment</hi> to them in their march through the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: This <hi>water</hi> and <hi>rock</hi> are Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>So the <hi>brazen Serpent,</hi> a ſtrange thing, to heal by <hi>look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> upon it, and that which otherwiſe might ſeem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable: This healing Serpent is <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo <hi>Aarons rod,</hi> a marvellous thing, for a dry rod to <hi>bud, bloſſom, and bring forth Almonds,</hi> is very ſtrange. This dry rod is Jeſus Chriſt, who, though a root out of a dry ground, yet doth daily <hi>bud, bloſſom,</hi> and <hi>bring forth:</hi> as he puts forth ſeveral <hi>degrees</hi> of life, <hi>holineſs</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> in the ſpirits of Saints.</p>
            <p>But I paſs this: And come next to look upon this <hi>wonderful</hi> perſon in a more direct, and immediate aſpect. And ſo we ſhall preſent him as three wayes <hi>Wonderful.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>In his <hi>Perſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In his <hi>Offices.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In his <hi>Works.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:40187:13"/>
            <p>1. Firſt in his <hi>Perſon:</hi> which is really (as it was hyperbolically affirmed of <hi>Dionyſius the Areopagite</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Treaſury of myſteries: He is <hi>wonderful</hi> as God, as Man, and as God-Man.</p>
            <p>1. As God: And I hope I have not to deal either with Arrians, or Socinians that deny it.</p>
            <p>In God there is nothing but what is infinite, incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible, and inconceivable, and therefore <hi>wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful:</hi> When we turn our eys upon <hi>Divinity,</hi> we are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſwallowed up. As thoſe <hi>waters of the Sanctuary</hi> we read of Ezek. 47. <hi>were firſt to the Ancles, and then to the Knees, and then to the Loyns, and then became waters that could not be paſſed over, waters to ſwim in:</hi> So as we aſcend from <hi>inferiour</hi> beings, to thoſe that are <hi>ſuperiour,</hi> we find the waters <hi>riſing</hi> higher and higher upon us, as we meet with perfections of a greater heighth and depth, till we arrive at the being of the <hi>ever bleſſed God,</hi> and there we are ſwallowed up.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Touching the Almighty,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob, We cannot find him out,</hi> Job 37. 23. And in ver. 19. <hi>We cannot order our ſpeech by reaſon of darkneſs:</hi> And ver. 20. <hi>If a man ſpeak, ſurely he ſhall be</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſwallowed up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of that which is called God (ſaith a Learned Ancient)<note place="margin">Penitus abſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebitur.</note> 
               <hi>Nec eſt ſenſus, nec ratio, nec judicium, nec phantaſia, nec</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dionyſ. Areopa.</note> 
               <hi>opinio:</hi> Neither ſence, reaſon, judgement, phanſie, or opinion can comprehend him.</p>
            <p>And the ſame Author in an Epiſtle to <hi>Caius</hi> the Monk hath this divine paſſage, <note n="*" place="margin">Quo propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ad deum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendimus, eo clarius cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcimus eum eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ſupra omnem cognitionem.</note> 
               <hi>By how much the nearer we come to God, the more clearly we know him to be above all knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bradwardine</hi> brings in ſeveral <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> giving ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral deſcriptions of God.</p>
            <p>One this, <hi>Deus eſt qui ſolâ ignoranti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mente concipitur<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:40187:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> God is beſt known by ignorance; for all knowledge falls <hi>infinitely</hi> ſhort of him: And therefore we beſt know him, when we come moſt fully to ſee that he cannot be known.</p>
            <p>Another this, <hi>Deus eſt tenebrae: poſt omnem lucem in mente relictae; That darkneſs or ignorance that is left in the mind after all its light:</hi> I conceive he meant, that what a man comprehends of <hi>God,</hi> that is not <hi>God,</hi> but that which is yet above him, hidden in the dark from him, that is <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Plato</hi> ſpeaks thus of him: <hi>The maker of this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe it is as hard to find out, as having found out to ſpeak worthily of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to leave his <hi>Divinity</hi> which doth over-match all finite underſtanding, we ſhall deſcend to his <hi>Humanity,</hi> and ſo we ſhall find him <hi>wonderful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. In the ſecond place as <hi>Man;</hi> He was indeed a <hi>man,</hi> but the <hi>Phoenix</hi> of the world, and <hi>None-ſuch,</hi> a <hi>wonderful</hi> man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wonderful</hi> in his Conception, formed by the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate <hi>finger</hi> of the Spirit, without the concurrence of any natural Plaſtique power from man; which <hi>David</hi> in his own perſon as the <hi>type</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>Pſal. 139. 14. I am fearfully, and wonderfully made:</hi> And therefore it was ſaid to the <hi>Virgin Mary, The power of the moſt High ſhall overſhadow thee;</hi> to imply, that Chriſt was to be formed in a <hi>dark, hidden,</hi> and <hi>myſterious</hi> way within her.</p>
            <p>And ſo he was a man <hi>wonderful</hi> in <hi>wiſdom;</hi> His <hi>wiſdom</hi> was <hi>wonderful,</hi> both in reſpect of the <hi>conveighance</hi> of it, and the <hi>extent,</hi> and <hi>perfection</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the <hi>conveighance,</hi> not attained by ſtudy, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, and inquiry, as Humane knowledge and wiſdom
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40187:14"/> ordinarily are: but immediatly <hi>deſcending</hi> upon him in the light of the <hi>Divinity; the Godhead</hi> opening it ſelf upon him, and pouring forth <hi>it ſelf</hi> into him. And therefore the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> tels us, <hi>that what Chriſt ſaw and heard, that he teſtified:</hi> He ſaw and heard all in God;<note place="margin">Joh. 3. 32.</note> which made the people to wonder at him; ſaying, <hi>Whence hath this man this wiſdom, not having known let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters?</hi> Mark 6. 2.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For the <hi>perfection</hi> of it; <hi>all the treaſures of wiſdom and knowledge were hid in him;</hi> when he was but a child, he was found in the Temple, <hi>diſputing with the Doctors, and putting them to ſilence;</hi> and we often read, that when the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes,</hi> and <hi>Doctors</hi> of the Law came to entrap him, by the wiſdom of his anſwers he delivered himſelf, and ſent them away aſhamed.</p>
            <p>And ſo further, he was a man <hi>wonderful</hi> in power; <hi>What manner of man is this,</hi> ſay the people, <hi>that the Winde and Seas obey him?</hi> Beloved, while you look upon him ſpeaking to the devils, and they tremble at his voyce; ſpeaking to the dead, and they riſe; to the graves, and they open; doth not this declare him a man <hi>wonderful</hi> in <hi>power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was alſo <hi>wonderful</hi> in his <hi>holineſs,</hi> a man without the leaſt <hi>tincture</hi> of ſin: and amidſt all the <hi>tentations</hi> and <hi>defilements</hi> of this world round about him, yet kept himſelf <hi>unſpotted</hi> and <hi>pure,</hi> never departing from his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> Will; never <hi>ſeeking</hi> himſelf in any one act, never ſo much as beholding any <hi>object</hi> through a falſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful notion.</p>
            <p>And all <hi>divine</hi> and <hi>heavenly perfection</hi> and <hi>vertues</hi> did ſhine forth in a <hi>wonderful</hi> manner in him; <hi>wonderful pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> ſtrange <hi>humility,</hi> unconceiveable <hi>mercy,</hi> aſtoniſhing <hi>kindneſs,</hi> and <hi>goodneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:40187:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>We might add alſo how he was <hi>wonderful</hi> at his death, when as <hi>the rocks rent, the graves opened, the dead aroſe, and darkneſs was upon the face of the earth:</hi> which made a <hi>learned</hi> man in thoſe times, cry out <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Diony. Areopagita. Vid. Tertul. Apologet.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>Either God ſuffers, or doth ſympathize with him that ſuffers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But thirdly, Conſidering him as <hi>God-man,</hi> ſo we ſhall again find <hi>wonderful</hi> things in him. Here in <hi>General,</hi> you may ſee the <hi>Eternal God,</hi> coming down into the loweſt <hi>depth</hi> of debaſement and humility, and frail man raiſed up into the <hi>higheſt pitch</hi> of dignity and glory; ſo that, as <hi>Divinity</hi> could not well ſtoop lower; ſo neither could <hi>Humanity</hi> be raiſed higher.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, Here we ſee, a poor low <hi>Creature,</hi> made one perſon with the <hi>higheſt God;</hi> two <hi>natures</hi> infinitely di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, yet ſo <hi>wonderfully</hi> united as to make one perſon. To ſee the <hi>Elements</hi> of differing and contrary qualities, to meet together in one <hi>compound</hi> body; to ſee the ſoul that is of a ſpiritual ſubſtance, to be in ſo near <hi>affinity</hi> and <hi>conjunction</hi> with an earthly body, is ſtrange; but to ſee <hi>God</hi> and man met together in one <hi>Perſon,</hi> is ſuch a <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery,</hi> that neither men nor Angels can comprehend.</p>
            <p>So that by vertue of this <hi>union,</hi> the <hi>properties</hi> of the <hi>Godhead</hi> are aſcribed to the <hi>Manhood;</hi> as to be Infinite, Omnipotent, &amp;c. And, the properties of the <hi>Manhood</hi> are attributed to the <hi>Godhead;</hi> as to ſhed blood, dye, and ſuffer, and the like.</p>
            <p>Yea, for the <hi>Creator</hi> to become a <hi>Creature;</hi> for the <hi>Eternal Spirit</hi> to be made <hi>Fleſh;</hi> for the <hi>Holy God</hi> to be made <hi>Sin;</hi> the <hi>Ever-bleſſed God,</hi> to be made a <hi>Curſe;</hi> the <hi>ſtrong God</hi> to become <hi>weak;</hi> the <hi>Lord of Life</hi> to dye: for riches and poverty, glory and ſhame, ſtrength and weakneſs, righteouſneſs and ſin, fulneſs and empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to meet thus together in this <hi>union,</hi> is ſuch a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40187:15"/> 
               <hi>Myſtery</hi> as ſwalloweth up all finite Underſtandings.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And Secondly, In this <hi>union</hi> again, we ſee <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> embracing; and that two ways. Firſt by way of Reconciliation, Chriſt in the <hi>nature</hi> of man, doth reconcile <hi>man</hi> and this whole <hi>Creation</hi> to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Col. 1. 20. By him to reconcile all things to himſelf, whether they be things in earth, or things in heaven.</hi> Secondly, by way of <hi>union,</hi> man being made one with God, who is in himſelf <hi>a little world,</hi> this whole <hi>Creation</hi> is come alſo into a <hi>union</hi> with God: Chriſt clothing himſelf with our <hi>nature,</hi> was, in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, inveſted with the whole <hi>Creation,</hi> and all his works did do him <hi>Homage</hi> and Service, and bring in praiſe and glory to him in the <hi>Man Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> The Apoſtle ſpeaks forth this <hi>Myſtery, Eph. 1. 10. That in the diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the fulneſs of times, he might gather together in one, all things which are in heaven, and which are on earth, even in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Incarnatio, eſt elevatio totius univerſi in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinam perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam.</note> 
               <hi>him.</hi> And, learned <hi>Cajetan,</hi> ſpeaks thus; ſaith he, <hi>The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation of Chriſt, is the lifting up of the whole <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe into the Divine perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, In this <hi>union,</hi> we ſee Man in the <hi>ſoveraignty</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of God: <hi>Man,</hi> exerciſing power and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over all the works of God; for the <hi>Humanity</hi> doth co-operate with the <hi>Divinity</hi> in ſwaying the <hi>Scepter,</hi> both of heaven and earth, <hi>Math. 28. 18. All power is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto me, both in Heaven and in Earth.</hi> And is not this <hi>wonderful,</hi> to ſee our <hi>Nature,</hi> ſitting upon the <hi>Throne</hi> of God, and <hi>raigning</hi> in the ſame authority and ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty with the <hi>Eternal God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, In this <hi>union,</hi> we yet ſee further <hi>wonders;</hi> we ſee the wonderful <hi>perfections</hi> of <hi>Almighty</hi> God ſhining forth in the higheſt and cleareſt <hi>diſcoveries</hi> of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the world. Though God is <hi>wonderful</hi> in all
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40187:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> his works: this <hi>fabrick</hi> of Heaven and Earth is a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful piece, and much of Gods glory appears in it; yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where is he ſo fully and gloriouſly <hi>declared</hi> as in the Man Chriſt Jeſus: ſo that the Angels themſelves, as it were, paſſing by the reſt of Gods works, do <hi>eſpecially</hi> gaze upon thoſe diſcoveries that God hath made of himſelf in Jeſus Chriſt: we read, 1 <hi>Pet. 1. 12. Epheſ.</hi> 3. 10. whether ye ſpeak of <hi>Mercy,</hi> or of <hi>Truth,</hi> or of <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> or of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> or of <hi>Power,</hi> or of <hi>Wiſdom:</hi> all theſe in an <hi>eminent</hi> and <hi>aſtoniſhing</hi> way ſhine forth in the Man Chriſt Jeſus. Thus we have ſhewed him firſt wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in his <hi>perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. In the ſecond place, we ſhal preſent him <hi>wonderful</hi> in his <hi>Offices,</hi> as <hi>King, Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Prophet:</hi> And it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their <hi>wonderful</hi> to ſee theſe three <hi>formally</hi> to meet in their <hi>higheſt</hi> perfection in one and the ſame perſon. <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ehizedeck,</hi> was a <hi>King</hi> and a <hi>Prieſt; Solomon</hi> a <hi>King</hi> and a <hi>Prophet; Samuel</hi> a <hi>Prieſt</hi> and a <hi>Prophet;</hi> but we read of none in whom all theſe <hi>Offices</hi> did <hi>formally</hi> meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but in Chriſt alone.</p>
            <p n="1">1. But to conſider them <hi>diſtinctly:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, He is a <hi>wonderful</hi> King; <hi>wonderful</hi> in reſpect of <hi>outward meanneſs;</hi> a great King, and yet in the <hi>meaneſt garb,</hi> in the loweſt ſtate; born a <hi>King,</hi> and yet <hi>laid in a Manger;</hi> a <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>yet had not where to lay his head;</hi> a <hi>King,</hi> and yet riding upon a poor ſilly Aſs: In nothing was he like the <hi>Kings</hi> of this world. The Thiefe upon the Croſs, deſires him, to <hi>remember him when he came into his Kingdom:</hi> to whom, I remember <hi>Auguſtine</hi> makes theſe witty Interrogatories, <hi>O thief, what royalty doſt thou ſee? Doſt thou ſee any other Crown on his head, but Thorns? any other Scepter in his hand, but nailes? any Throne, but a Croſs? any Purple, but Blood? any Guard,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40187:16"/> but Executioners?</hi> Again, A <hi>ſtrange King,</hi> if you look upon his <hi>anointing:</hi> The Spirit was that <hi>oyl</hi> wherewith he was <hi>annointed</hi> of God: and the Scepter he ſways is a ſtrange Scepter; other Scepters are of gold and ſilver, but Chriſts Scepter is, the <hi>word of his mouth;</hi> by this, he <hi>ſlays the wicked,</hi> deſtroys the <hi>Man of ſin,</hi> ſubdues the <hi>hearts</hi> of men to himſelf: other <hi>Scepters</hi> only reach the outward man, but this puts forth its <hi>authority</hi> in the ſoul: by it he <hi>writes his Law in the heart,</hi> which no other King can do: This Scepter not only <hi>kils,</hi> but <hi>makes alive;</hi> not only <hi>wounds,</hi> but heales not only lays <hi>commands</hi> on men, but gives heart and power to <hi>obey</hi> thoſe Commands, which no other <hi>Scepter</hi> can do.</p>
            <p>Again, He is a <hi>ſtrange King,</hi> if ye look upon the nature of his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which conſiſts not in outward <hi>pompe, magnificence</hi> and <hi>ſtate,</hi> worldly honors, riches, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights as the Kingdoms of this world, <hi>but in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 17.</note> 
               <hi>peace, and joy in the holy Ghoſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Its Power, Majeſty, and Glory, is ſet up and appears in the <hi>hearts</hi> of men. Neither is it carried on in a way <hi>viſible</hi> to ſenſe, for <hi>it comes not with obſervation,</hi> but ſecretly and ſilently with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out noiſe or tumult <hi>inſinuates</hi> its ſelf into the ſpirits of men, and is ſubduing the world before it. This <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> in times of want, ſuffering, and perſecution, when the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of this world are whithering and falling, is then uſually in the moſt riſing and floriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing State; neither is it upheld by the <hi>power</hi> of <hi>ſword,</hi> weapons of <hi>war,</hi> the <hi>Authority</hi> and Laws of Princes, but by the power of the <hi>Eternal Spirit,</hi> by <hi>the word of Chriſts mouth,</hi> and that when the <hi>powers</hi> of this world have ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ingaged againſt it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, If you look upon his <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> He is a wonderful <hi>Prieſt:</hi> He is ſo a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> as that he is alſo the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40187:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Altar</hi> and the <hi>Sacrifice:</hi> the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> is the <hi>Humanity,</hi> the <hi>Altar</hi> is the <hi>Divinity;</hi> the <hi>Prieſt</hi> is both theſe in their union; for he himſelf as <hi>God-man,</hi> offers up himſelf as man, upon himſelf as <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſaid, <hi>Judges</hi> 3. 19. that in the Sacrifice which <hi>Manoah</hi> offered up to the Lord, <hi>The Angel of God did wonderouſly: The Angel aſcended in the flame of the Altar;</hi> which did repreſent Chriſt offering up himſelf as a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,</hi> in the <hi>flame</hi> of his own love, and the fire of his Fathers wrath; In which <hi>Sacrifice</hi> he did indeed do <hi>wonderouſly, made an end of ſin, brought in everlaſting righteouſneſs,</hi> reconciled man and the whole <hi>Creation</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Father, and <hi>for ever perfected them that are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied:</hi> Other Prieſts had an outward conſecration, anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, waſhing, outward ornaments and attire, as a Mitre, Breaſtplate, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim and Thummim,</hi> an embroidered coat, an Ephod and Girdle, &amp;c. but Chriſt had <hi>none</hi> of theſe, and yet had all theſe in a ſpiritual and tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent way.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, as a <hi>Prophet,</hi> he was <hi>wonderful</hi> alſo; ſuch a <hi>Prophet</hi> as hath his <hi>chair</hi> in the hearts of men: A <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> that not alone preſents <hi>divine</hi> truth to us, but gives light and underſtanding for the <hi>receiving</hi> of the truth he doth preſent: A <hi>Prophet</hi> that not only <hi>ſpeaks out</hi> truth, but brings the ſoul under the <hi>power and obedience</hi> of what he ſpeaks; that <hi>unites</hi> truth and the ſoul together,<note place="margin">Chriſtus eſt qui docet &amp; doce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> and <hi>transforms</hi> it into the very nature of it: Yea, he is both the <hi>Teacher</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> taught. This is the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of <hi>Theology</hi> above all other <hi>Sciences;</hi> That the <hi>perſon</hi> teaching, and the <hi>thing taught,</hi> are both one and the ſame. Thus we have ſhewed him wonderful in his <hi>Offices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, He is alſo <hi>wonderful</hi> in his <hi>works;</hi> If you ſpeak
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40187:17"/> firſt, of the works of <hi>Creation,</hi> his wonderfulneſs ſhines forth here<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> There is not the leaſt <hi>creature</hi> but ſpeaks out this <hi>Name</hi> of his. And here I might lead you into the hidden <hi>ſecrets</hi> of Nature, and read you a large Lecture of <hi>Natural Philoſophy;</hi> were it a work ſutable to this place and Auditory: And further, I might carry you along through the works of <hi>Providence,</hi> and ſhew you the wonderful <hi>adminiſtration</hi> of the things of this world; with what admirable <hi>Wiſdom, Truth, Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> they are all managed; every Providence, though never ſo ſtrange, uncouth, and improbable, yet by Jeſus Chriſt made to centre in his <hi>Fathers</hi> glory, and his <hi>Churches</hi> good.</p>
            <p>And ſo we might paſs to the work of <hi>Redemption,</hi> and ſhew you how <hi>wonderfully</hi> he hath raiſed up <hi>ſalvation</hi> to his people. How <hi>wonderfully Satan</hi> is conquered, <hi>ſin done away, righteouſneſs</hi> brought in, <hi>Juſtice</hi> ſatisfied: all the <hi>deſigns</hi> of God, and the <hi>neceſsities</hi> of man fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in this glorious work. Would you ſee the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of it? in one word, it is this, God coming down into <hi>Communion</hi> with man in his ſin, ſhame, weakneſs and miſery; and then drawing up man into <hi>Communion</hi> with himſelf in his own Righteouſneſs, Power, Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs and Glory: <hi>God</hi> departing for a ſeaſon out of his <hi>Glory,</hi> and then riſing up into it again, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying man into the ſame <hi>glory</hi> with himſelf; as <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> boldly expreſſeth it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>God was made man, that man might be deified in himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when he comes actually to bring forth this <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption</hi> within us, and to accompliſh the work of <hi>ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> in the ſouls of men; here he is <hi>wonderful</hi> again when he comes and ſets up a <hi>glorious light</hi> in the midſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40187:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> of that <hi>thick darkneſs</hi> that before did cover us; when he comes and opens the <hi>door</hi> of mans heart that was faſt ſhut up againſt him, turns the <hi>will</hi> and <hi>the affections</hi> into quite contrary channels, yea, turns upſide down the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry frame and <hi>foundation</hi> of corrupt nature; throws down the <hi>powers of darkneſs, diſſolves all the works of the devil,</hi> and ſets up a new <hi>Creation</hi> purely upon a new bottom, erecteth a beautiful <hi>ſtructure</hi> of righteouſneſs and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and a ſpiritual <hi>Temple</hi> to the Lord in the midſt of that rubbiſh of confuſion, deſolation, and diſorder that was there before; and all this by the meer power of his word; He that doth theſe things, his name is and ſhall be called <hi>wonderful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things I briefly paſs over, that I might not be too much ſtraitned in the <hi>Application,</hi> where I ſhall ſpeak ſomething further of them.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>Application.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vſe.</hi> 1. This may firſt ſerve for <hi>Invitation,</hi> to draw in ſouls to Jeſus Chriſt: Firſt, you that are ſtrangers, me thinks your hearts ſhould be powerfully <hi>drawn</hi> to Chriſt, by that diſcovery we have now made of him. Things <hi>wonderful,</hi> every man hath a ſecret natural itch and appetite to be prying into, and inquiring after. Things common and ordinary, we ſlight and paſs by; but what is <hi>wonderful,</hi> that we are apt to gaze upon. When the <hi>Sun</hi> is eclipſed, though then it hath leſſer glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, yet becauſe there is ſome <hi>ſtrangeneſs</hi> in that appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, every mans eye is turned upon it: So, although when we tell you of the <hi>glorious beauty</hi> of Chriſt, and endeavour to ſet this before you, your <hi>ſouls</hi> are not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved towards him, yet becauſe we tell you there is a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40187:18"/> 
                  <hi>wonderfulneſs</hi> in him, let this draw your eys and your hearts to him: Many men are of <hi>contemplative</hi> ſpirits, who delight to enquire into the knowledge of things hidden and ſecret; here in Jeſus Chriſt are the higheſt <hi>myſteries,</hi> and the greateſt <hi>rarities</hi> that Heaven and Earth can afford. Was not this that which drew the <hi>Queen of Sheba from the uttermoſt parts of the Earth,</hi> the report which ſhe heard of the wonderful <hi>wiſdom</hi> of King <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon?</hi> And do not <hi>ſtories</hi> tell us, that men came from all parts of the earth to behold the <hi>rare beauty</hi> of <hi>Pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lope?</hi> But yet, lo, <hi>A greater then Solomon is here,</hi> one in whom <hi>are hid all the treaſures of wiſdom and knowledge,</hi> and a <hi>beauty</hi> which that of <hi>Penelope</hi> was ſcarce a ſhadow of. Oh that men would come to feed and to feaſt their ſouls in the contemplation of thoſe rare excellencies, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and perfections, which are <hi>treaſured up</hi> in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Yea, here are all <hi>perfections,</hi> not only to gaze upon, but to be <hi>improved</hi> for your ſalvation and happineſs. Here is <hi>wonderful mercy</hi> ſhal be improved to pardon thee; <hi>wonderful grace</hi> to accept and entertain thee: <hi>wondrous goodneſs</hi> to relieve and ſupply thee: <hi>wonderful power</hi> to redeem and ſupport thee: <hi>wonderful wiſdom</hi> to inſtruct and guide thee: and <hi>wonderful holineſs</hi> to adorn and ſanctifie thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and <hi>wonderful fulneſs</hi> to fill and ſatisfie thee.</p>
               <p>And as for you who already know him; ſeeing he is <hi>wonderful,</hi> be you ſtill ſearching and enquiring into him; his <hi>Perſon,</hi> his <hi>Offices,</hi> his <hi>Works,</hi> for in all he is <hi>wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</hi> Things that are wonderful, have a <hi>heighth, depth,</hi> and <hi>bredth</hi> in them, not eaſily diſcovered: and the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we ſearch into this <hi>great myſterie,</hi> the Lord Jeſus, the more will his <hi>wonderfulneſs</hi> ſhine forth upon us:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40187:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> And though we may ſee an end of all <hi>created perfection;</hi> yet in him there is ſtill a perfection beyond our reach to entertain our admiration. <hi>Solomon</hi> doth adviſe us to <hi>ſeek after wiſdom as ſilver, and to ſearch after her as hidden treaſure:</hi> This wiſdom is our <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> in whom all the <hi>treaſures</hi> of heaven are hidden and laid up; and are diſcovered unto thoſe ſpirits that are in the power and light of God <hi>ſearching</hi> into them: The Apoſtle in the third to the <hi>Epheſ.</hi> having ſpoken in the beginning of the Chapter of the great <hi>myſterie of Chriſt which was hid in God,</hi> comes to pray in <hi>ver.</hi> 18. that the Epheſians <hi>might be able with all Saints to comprehend what is the heighth, depth, length and breadth:</hi> In natural things there are but three dimenſions, <hi>length, breadth and depth:</hi> but here are <hi>four</hi> for Saints to be daily exerciſed in the comprehending of.</p>
               <p>Oh that therefore you would bend your <hi>thoughts</hi> hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and fix your <hi>contemplation</hi> upon the <hi>wonders</hi> of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt! Eſpecially conſidering, that Chriſt hath this name <hi>Wonderful</hi> given him in order to your <hi>ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and as he is <hi>the Saviour</hi> of his people: So that you do but diſcover the <hi>treaſures</hi> of your own comfort, happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and glory, while you are enquiring and ſearching into him. As you finde him a <hi>rich Mine,</hi> and <hi>unſearchable riches</hi> treaſured up in him: ſo are they <hi>all</hi> laid out upon your ſalvation. As the <hi>eye</hi> of your ſoul goes before, and makes <hi>diſcovery;</hi> ſo <hi>Faith,</hi> the hand of your ſoul, may follow after, and take hold of what is <hi>diſcovered.</hi> He that is <hi>heir apparent</hi> to the Crown, looks upon the <hi>Majeſty, Royalty</hi> and <hi>Riches</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> with another eye then a <hi>meer</hi> ſtranger; the one may <hi>gaze</hi> upon them, and wonder; but the other doth behold them as in a <hi>propriety,</hi> and ſo doth <hi>ſecretly</hi> poſſeſs them, <hi>rejoyce</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> in them.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:40187:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. If the Lord Jeſus be thus <hi>wonderful,</hi> then let us not <hi>circumſcribe</hi> and limit him; not confine and meaſure him by our <hi>narrow</hi> underſtanding; ſeeing he is in every reſpect <hi>wonderful.</hi> And,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Take heed of limiting his <hi>Perſon,</hi> by framing mean and low <hi>conceptions</hi> of thoſe <hi>immenſe</hi> perfections that are in himſelf: we are apt to <hi>conceive</hi> of him, by what we ſee in the creature, and to meaſure the <hi>Infinite</hi> by the <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite:</hi> his infinite beauty, mercy, ſweetneſs, and wiſdom by what we ſee of theſe <hi>among</hi> the creatures below: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Jeſus Chriſt hath all theſe <hi>perfections</hi> of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in himſelf, but in ſuch an <hi>eminent</hi> and <hi>tranſcendent</hi> manner, as no created underſtanding can reach. <hi>To whom will you liken the Lord,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>or what likeneſs will you compare unto him?</hi> Iſa. 40. 18. And there is <hi>nothing</hi> that can be <hi>compared</hi> to him, in Heaven or Earth: And therefore when thou falleſt down before him to <hi>worſhip</hi> him, take heed of repreſenting him to thy ſelf under any <hi>created form,</hi> leſt thou worſhip an <hi>Idol</hi> ſet up in thy brain inſtead of God. <hi>Si quis viſo Deo, cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit id quod vidit, non illum vidit,</hi> ſaith a Learned man: Thou that ſayeſt, thou ſeeſt God, if thou doſt <hi>Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend</hi> what thou ſeeſt, thou ſeeſt not God; for he is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely <hi>above all</hi> comprehenſion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Take heed of limiting him in reſpect of his <hi>work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> for he is herein alſo <hi>wonderful:</hi> Which ſpeaks out three things:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Preſcribe him not his <hi>way,</hi> dictate not to him his <hi>method;</hi> for if we do, we limit him: He will accompliſh his own deſigns and end, but haply in ſuch a way as thou didſt never imagine: for, he is <hi>wonderful. Who</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 40. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>hath directed the Spirit of the Lord, or being his Counſellor hath taught him?</hi> ſaith the Prophet. In nothing is God
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40187:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> more wonderful, then in the <hi>path</hi> and <hi>method</hi> wherein he walks: And this is that which many <hi>forward Profeſſors</hi> in our dayes have been offended at; having <hi>preſcribed</hi> to God his way, wherein they intended to follow him, he chooſing out another-way to himſelf, they have then <hi>deſerted</hi> him, and departed from him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Again, do not <hi>diſtruſt</hi> him, for then we limit him: As the Iſraelites thus <hi>limited</hi> God; <hi>Can God</hi> (ſay they) <hi>prepare a Table in the wilderneſs?</hi> Can he give us <hi>water</hi> in this dry and thirſty Land? We forget <hi>this name of his</hi> in the <hi>Text,</hi> when ever we <hi>diſtruſt</hi> him: we ſay indeed that he is <hi>Almighty,</hi> and <hi>Al-ſufficient,</hi> but when we come into ſuch extremities that <hi>Almightineſs</hi> muſt help us or nothing, how do our hearts faint and die within us? He is wonderful in <hi>Counſel</hi> to guide thee, in <hi>Power</hi> to ſupport thee, in <hi>Mercy</hi> to pardon thee, in <hi>Goodneſs</hi> to ſupply thee; and therefore diſtruſt him not. Thou haply ſeeſt the work of thy ſalvation encountred with great <hi>difficulties,</hi> and ſtrong <hi>oppoſition,</hi> and great mountains laid in the way of <hi>Sions</hi> glory: yet let the remembrance of this name of his ſupport thy faith againſt them all.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Do not <hi>cenſure</hi> him: when he hath put thy <hi>reaſon</hi> to a ſtand, and is quite gone out of thy ſight, and is do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his work under <hi>the dark clouds,</hi> that thou canſt not ſee him, and where thou wouldſt <hi>leaſt look for him,</hi> cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure him not: for, he is <hi>wonderful.</hi> He will anſwer the <hi>prayers</hi> of his people, and work out the ſalvation of <hi>Sion,</hi> but in a way that few ſhall be able to bear.</p>
               <p>We have cryed and prayed for <hi>Juſtice,</hi> for <hi>Reformation,</hi> for the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt, the <hi>throwing down</hi> the <hi>Man of Sin:</hi> but few of us knew what <hi>indeed</hi> we prayed for; and therefore when God hath been giving in theſe things to us, though not <hi>according</hi> to our <hi>apprehenſions</hi> of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40187:20"/> them, the ſame <hi>zeal</hi> hath been <hi>improved againſt them</hi> as was before <hi>for them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo we now pray for the <hi>converſion</hi> of the Jews; but happy is <hi>that man</hi> that ſhall be able <hi>to ſtand to</hi> his own prayers, when God ſhall come <hi>to effect</hi> this; for it will be <hi>ſuch a time of trouble, as hath never been ſince there was a Nation</hi> as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 1. And the work may be done in ſuch a way, as that <hi>thoſe men</hi> that have prayed for it, may then oppoſe it. I know many men who now pray for the converſion of the Jews, and yet would be ready <hi>to oppoſe</hi> their coming <hi>to live</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us; which may yet ſeem to be the moſt proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble way of effecting it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. If Jeſus Chriſt be wonderful, let us learn to have <hi>high expectations</hi> of him; let this give <hi>life</hi> to our hopes, and <hi>wings</hi> to our faith: thou haſt <hi>great works</hi> to be done within thee, <hi>great corruptions</hi> to be ſubdued; <hi>great temptations</hi> conquered; <hi>great wants</hi> to be ſupplied; and ſo there are yet <hi>great works</hi> to be done in the world, the peace of <hi>Sion</hi> to be eſtabliſhed, the throne of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> to be demoliſhed, the <hi>Nations</hi> to be called and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, the <hi>Goſpel</hi> to be propagated, <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> to be deſtroyed; <hi>judgement</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> to be ſetled in the Earth; that <hi>nothing</hi> but wonderful <hi>power</hi> and <hi>wiſdom</hi> is able, to accompliſh <hi>theſe things;</hi> yet, let our expectations be kept up <hi>to the heighth;</hi> for here is <hi>One</hi> whoſe name is <hi>Wonderful,</hi> is ingaged in them: And we ſhall ſee <hi>this name</hi> of his, written upon the <hi>inſtruments</hi> whereby he works, and upon the <hi>method</hi> wherein he walks, and upon the <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>perfection</hi> of the <hi>works</hi> themſelves when they are <hi>brought to paſs;</hi> His works all along ſhall <hi>ſavor</hi> of this name of his.</p>
               <p>Our expectation of a perſon, is uſually, according to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40187:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> his abilities; <hi>as the man is, ſo is his ſtrength;</hi> and as his <hi>ſtrength</hi> is, ſo are <hi>his actings:</hi> what manner <hi>of ſalvation</hi> may <hi>Saints</hi> then <hi>expect</hi> from ſuch a <hi>wonderful</hi> perſon, as Jeſus Chriſt, and who will <hi>ingrave</hi> this Name of his in <hi>viſible</hi> Characters all along upon it!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4. If Jeſus Chriſt be thus <hi>wonderful,</hi> then ſure it is both his <hi>expectation,</hi> and our <hi>duty,</hi> to <hi>wonder</hi> at him. Let us learn then, <hi>ſilently</hi> to ſit down and <hi>wonder</hi> at what we cannot <hi>comprehend.</hi> Sure this is the <hi>great end</hi> of God, in all thoſe <hi>wonderful appearances</hi> of his, in the Lord Jeſus, to put <hi>the hearts of his poor people</hi> for ever, into a <hi>ſweet</hi> aſtoniſhment.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid of Chriſt at his glorious appearance, that <hi>he ſhal come to be admired in all that believe, 2 Theſ.</hi> 1, 10. He ſhall appear every way <hi>wonderful;</hi> and the <hi>proper</hi> and genuine <hi>entertainment</hi> of wonderful things, is <hi>to wonder at them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We never better <hi>find</hi> Chriſt, then when we do moſt <hi>loſe our ſelves</hi> in him: This divine admiration is that <hi>ſacred mount</hi> which the ſoul aſcending, <hi>there</hi> enjoys the cleareſt <hi>viſion</hi> of God, and <hi>ſweeteſt</hi> communion with him. Therefore let us <hi>ſet apart</hi> ſome time, every day, to go up into <hi>this mount of viſion,</hi> retiring our ſelves from our ſelves, and all things <hi>viſible</hi> and <hi>ſecular,</hi> and divine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>gaze</hi> upon theſe <hi>wonderful things</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, till we find a ſweet <hi>amazement</hi> ſeizing upon <hi>all the powers</hi> of the ſoul, and carrying them forth into a divine exta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. And,</p>
               <p>Firſt, Look upon his <hi>perſon,</hi> and wonder there; look upon him firſt, in <hi>the glory</hi> of his Divinity, and <hi>loſe thy ſelf</hi> in it, as in a <hi>ſea</hi> of ſweetneſs and pleaſures: purſue thy thoughts, till thou arriveſt at <hi>infinity,</hi> and there <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to loſe thy ſelf;</hi> for the more thou knoweſt of God, the more ſhalt thou be <hi>better able</hi> to ſee, that he is <hi>above all knowledge.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:40187:21"/>
               <p>The mind of man hath <hi>three degrees</hi> of the knowledge of God, as a <hi>Learned man</hi> hath obſerved. In the <hi>firſt degree</hi> it uſeth many words of God; in the <hi>ſecond</hi> fewer; in the third <hi>none</hi> at all, but is <hi>ſtricken dumb</hi> with ſilence; as ſeeing all <hi>words</hi> falling infinitely ſhort of him: As <hi>Job,</hi> he was at his <hi>firſt</hi> diſcourſe with God <hi>full of words,</hi> whiles he knew him only <hi>by the hearing of the Ear;</hi> but after a more clear ſight and knowledge, <hi>words fail him,</hi> and he lies down <hi>dumb</hi> at the <hi>feet</hi> of God, ſaying, <hi>Once have I ſpoken, but I will no more; yea twiſe, but I will proceed no further.</hi> Job 40. 5.</p>
               <p>That <hi>you</hi> may be upon ſome <hi>advantage</hi> for this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Work; we ſhall briefly ſet ſome of the <hi>divine perfections</hi> of Chriſt before you; and then <hi>forbear</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring if you can.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Look upon his <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and wonder; his knowing <hi>all things</hi> paſt, preſent, and to come, <hi>open</hi> and <hi>ſecret,</hi> certain, and contingent; that which <hi>ſhall be,</hi> that which ſhall <hi>never be;</hi> and all this not by <hi>ſpecies,</hi> or infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation from others, but immediately <hi>by himſelf;</hi> not by <hi>ſucceſsion,</hi> but <hi>all</hi> at <hi>once;</hi> not by <hi>diſcourſe</hi> or reaſon, but in one <hi>ſimple intuitive</hi> act: what <hi>wonderful knowledge</hi> is this!</p>
               <p>Then look upon <hi>his Immenſity,</hi> and wonder, being one who <hi>containeth</hi> all things, and yet is <hi>contained</hi> of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: <hi>comprehendeth</hi> all things, and yet is himſelf <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible,</hi> whom <hi>the heavens, yea, the heaven of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens cannot contain, whoſe centre is everywhere, and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference nowhere,</hi> as an Heathen ſpeaks of God; ſo that his preſence is <hi>as much</hi> with one creature <hi>as with all,</hi> and with all <hi>as with one;</hi> is as much in one place as all; in all <hi>places</hi> as one: what a <hi>wonderful perſon</hi> is this!</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:40187:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>And ſo look upon his <hi>Eternity</hi> and wonder. Eternity (as the Schools define it) is, <hi>Interminabilis, &amp; tota ſimul vitae poſſeſsio; The poſſeſsion of an endleſs life all at once.</hi> Time it is <hi>Nunc fluens,</hi> but <hi>Eternity</hi> is <hi>Nunc ſtans,</hi> an <hi>everlaſting moment;</hi> whereby, Chriſt (conſidered <hi>as God</hi>) poſſeſſeth his own <hi>endleſs life</hi> in one moment: ſo that, there is <hi>nothing paſt</hi> to him, nothing <hi>future,</hi> but <hi>both parts of Eternity</hi> (as Divines ſpeak) and <hi>all things</hi> that have been, are, or ſhall be betwixt theſe <hi>two parts</hi> are <hi>actually</hi> preſent, and that <hi>continually</hi> before <hi>his face.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then turn your eyes, and look upon him in his <hi>Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity,</hi> and wonder; In the <hi>Divinity</hi> (which we are now ſpeaking to) there is no manner of <hi>diviſion, compoſition,</hi> or <hi>alterity</hi> at all; though we are ready both to <hi>divide,</hi> it, and <hi>compound</hi> it through the <hi>weakneſs</hi> of our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; here <hi>Wiſdom</hi> is <hi>the ſame</hi> thing with <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> with <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> with <hi>Mercy:</hi> nay, there is not <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>form, actus &amp; potentia, eſſence</hi> and <hi>opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in him: the <hi>power</hi> by which he acts, and the <hi>act</hi> it ſelf, are <hi>all one</hi> in God. As <hi>God</hi> loving himſelf, the <hi>loving,</hi> the <hi>loved,</hi> and the <hi>love,</hi> that is the band of both, is all, but one and the ſame thing.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, to go no further here: look upon him in his <hi>Eminency</hi> and wonder, as having all the <hi>perfections</hi> of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry creature, from the higheſt to the loweſt <hi>Eminently</hi> in himſelf, they being <hi>all</hi> but <hi>dark beams</hi> of that <hi>divine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> whereof he is <hi>the Sun</hi> from which they proceed, and upon which they do depend, and are <hi>infinitely,</hi> as in the <hi>firſt cauſe</hi> comprehended <hi>in himſelf.</hi> As <hi>Xeuxis,</hi> when he drew the Picture of <hi>Helena,</hi> had all the beautiful Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins of <hi>Greece</hi> before him; and whatever ſtamp of beauty or comlineſs he ſaw in any, put all into that one Picture: ſo all the ſeveral ſtamps and lineaments of beauty which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40187:22"/> are ſcattered up and down through the whole Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are all gathered up in a tranſcendent manner in the perſon of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And to look lower, down upon his <hi>Humanity,</hi> and there <hi>wonder at thoſe rare perfections</hi> and <hi>eminent</hi> graces that dwell in it: look upon <hi>it</hi> as the <hi>Repreſentative</hi> of all the Saints, the <hi>Epitome</hi> of the whole Creation; behold <hi>it</hi> in that intimate and immediate <hi>conjunction</hi> it hath with the <hi>Godhead:</hi> and here <hi>wonder to ſee</hi> how <hi>heaven</hi> and <hi>earth</hi> embrace: the <hi>Humanity</hi> raiſed <hi>infinitely</hi> high; the <hi>Divinity</hi> ſtooping <hi>infinitley</hi> low: God coming down <hi>in this humanity</hi> unto us; and <hi>through it</hi> raiſing us up unto <hi>himſelf,</hi> and his own <hi>life, bleſſedneſs</hi> and <hi>fulneſs,</hi> as we ſpake before;</p>
               <p>And then paſs on to his Works, and admire him <hi>there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, the works of <hi>Creation,</hi> for <hi>this name</hi> of his in the <hi>Text</hi> is viſibly <hi>written</hi> there: here are as well <hi>myſteries</hi> for admiration, as <hi>cauſes</hi> for reaſon, even ſuch as have <hi>non-pluſt</hi> the deepeſt <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> and the ableſt <hi>Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts:</hi> ſo that the <hi>creatures</hi> are not (as the Papiſts ſay of their Images) <hi>Idiotarum libri,</hi> books for <hi>Idiots</hi> only, but <hi>Cabinets of wonders</hi> for the higheſt Schollers and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> to admire. <hi>David</hi> ſpeaking of theſe <hi>works</hi> of God, in the 104. <hi>Pſal.</hi> His heart was <hi>ſo full,</hi> that he is faint in the midſt of his diſcourſe to <hi>ſtand ſtill,</hi> and wonder; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as in the 24. verſ. <hi>O Lord, how manifold are thy works, in wiſdom haſt thou made them all.</hi> And <hi>Elihu</hi> calls upon <hi>Job,</hi> Chap. 37. 14. <hi>Hearken, O</hi> Job, <hi>ſtand ſtill, and conſider the wonderful works of God.</hi> And <hi>God</hi> preſenting theſe before him, drove him into a ſpeechleſs ſilence; as we read, <hi>Job 40. 4. I will lay my hand upon my mouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Agur, Prov.</hi> 30. 4. looking upon the <hi>Creation,</hi> wonders at the <hi>Creator; Who hath aſcended up into heaven,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40187:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> or deſcended; who hath gathered the wind with his fiſts, who hath bound the waters in a garment, who hath eſtabliſhed all the ends of the earth? What is his name, or his Sons name, if thou canſt tell?</hi> And give me leave by way of <hi>imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of this holy man, to propound ſome queſtions to you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is it that props up the heavens that they fall not; and what hidden vertue or quality wherles them about in ſuch a rapid and regular motion? Whence is it? That the Sun, Moon, and Stars ſend their light, heat, and influence down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, when it is more natural for light and heat to aſcend upward? What is it? that gives the Rain-bow its various co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and bends it through the sky like a bowe? What is that? which thunders in the clouds, and ratleth like a Chariot in the heavens? Whence hath the wind its force, and out of what treaſury is it brought forth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to come yet lower: <hi>Whereupon are the foundations of the earth faſtened, and what Axel tree bears up the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of it? Whence is the ebbing and flowing of the ſea; and why do not the proud waves thereof overflow the bancks, when as they riſe many degrees above them?</hi> Whoſe power and wiſdom <hi>hath done</hi> all theſe things, <hi>what is his name, or his ſons name, if thou canſt tell?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Make this heavenly advantage of your <hi>Country houſes,</hi> as to admire the <hi>wonders of God</hi> that ſhine forth there round about you. Every <hi>Flower</hi> in the Garden, <hi>Tree</hi> in the Orchard, thoſe ſeveral <hi>beauties</hi> wherewith thou ſeeſt the Earth <hi>bedecked,</hi> may repreſent this <hi>wonderful one</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt in a delightfull <hi>appearance</hi> to thee: who is the <hi>ſweetneſs</hi> of all things <hi>ſweet:</hi> the <hi>beauty</hi> of all things <hi>beautiful:</hi> the <hi>glory</hi> of all things <hi>glorious.</hi> Yea, who is the <hi>form</hi> of every <hi>form,</hi> the <hi>life</hi> of all <hi>lives:</hi> that <hi>One Eternal root</hi> and <hi>ſeed,</hi> out of which all other <hi>ſeeds</hi> and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40187:23"/> 
                  <hi>roots</hi> do originally ſpring. And all that <hi>multiplicity, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, contrariety</hi> which is ſeen in things here below, do <hi>meet</hi> in the greateſt <hi>ſimplicity</hi> and <hi>unity</hi> in him: for it is <hi>unity</hi> that brought forth <hi>plurality:</hi> and all <hi>plurality</hi> is eminently comprehended in <hi>unity.</hi> And therefore, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> hath as it were multiplyed himſelf into ſuch <hi>various</hi> beauties, forms, and images, let us <hi>by theſe</hi> riſe up <hi>above</hi> theſe, unto himſelf who is <hi>all,</hi> and <hi>infinitely</hi> more then <hi>all theſe.</hi> And endeavour in the moſt <hi>ſimple</hi> and <hi>abſtracted</hi> acts of the mind, <hi>to cloſe</hi> with him, who is the moſt <hi>ſimple</hi> and <hi>abſtracted</hi> being; aſcending from the <hi>finite</hi> to the <hi>infinite,</hi> from the <hi>viſible</hi> to the <hi>inviſible,</hi> from the <hi>corruptible</hi> to that which is <hi>eternal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then, paſs on to the <hi>works</hi> of <hi>Providence,</hi> and <hi>wonder again</hi> here: Providence, it is <hi>Ordinatio rerum ad finem,</hi> as <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſpeaks: And it is wonderful to ſee how <hi>providence</hi> doth <hi>ſweetly</hi> diſpoſe of all things to their proper ends. As, we ſee in a <hi>Watch,</hi> the <hi>wheels</hi> are <hi>many,</hi> their <hi>motions</hi> various and contrary; that an unskilful man ſees no <hi>reaſon</hi> or <hi>method</hi> in them: but the <hi>wiſe</hi> Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer ſees <hi>method</hi> and <hi>reaſon</hi> in all. So <hi>divine providence,</hi> in a <hi>ſecret</hi> and <hi>inviſible</hi> way, guides the ſeveral, croſs, and interfering motions of the creature, with much <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>harmony,</hi> to their due and proper end.</p>
               <p>And here I might lead you back into the <hi>Story</hi> of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, and ſhew you the <hi>wonders</hi> of providence in the ſeveral Ages of the world; and in what a ſtrange <hi>method</hi> it hath carryed on the <hi>affairs</hi> of the Nations: eſpecially thoſe that have more immediatly referred to his <hi>Church;</hi> how <hi>wonderfully</hi> it hath been preſerved, as <hi>a Lamb</hi> in the midſt of <hi>Wolves,</hi> as a little <hi>ſpark</hi> of fire in the midſt of thoſe <hi>impetuous waves</hi> of perſecution that have every <hi>moment</hi> threatned to overwhelm her: Yea,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40187:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> and how in all <hi>Ages,</hi> God hath made the <hi>malice</hi> and <hi>policy</hi> of her enemies to conduce to her <hi>further</hi> ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and riſing in the world.</p>
               <p>But we need go <hi>no further</hi> then our own <hi>Nation,</hi> and theſe <hi>latter</hi> years; wherein God hath carryed on the <hi>affairs</hi> of his people, by a continued <hi>ſeries</hi> of wonders.</p>
               <p>To extirpate that <hi>Prelatical power</hi> that had ſo deeply riveted it ſelf into the <hi>bowels</hi> of the Nation, and yet the Nation ſtand, is <hi>wonderful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To raiſe up the <hi>heads</hi> of a: few <hi>contemptible</hi> men, the <hi>People of God</hi> in this Nation, called <hi>Puritans</hi> in the <hi>dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect</hi> of late times, and ſince put under <hi>other</hi> diſguizes, to repreſent the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſe up theſe, and make them to become a <hi>terrour</hi> to their enemies, though far <hi>more</hi> and <hi>mightier</hi> in outward ſtrength then they, is again <hi>wonderful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And further, to conſider what <hi>eminent</hi> acts of <hi>Juſtice</hi> have been done upon men of the <hi>higheſt rank,</hi> of the greateſt power, and intereſt.</p>
               <p>What changes have been made in Government, both <hi>Martial</hi> and <hi>Civil;</hi> putting both into new <hi>forms,</hi> and <hi>models;</hi> and <hi>all this</hi> to be done without the loſs and deſtruction of both, is, <hi>to conſidering men,</hi> ſtrange and wonderful.</p>
               <p>As alſo to behold what mighty <hi>Armies</hi> have been <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued,</hi> what impregnable <hi>Forts</hi> gained, what deep and deſperate <hi>Plots</hi> diſcovered, what eminent <hi>Victories</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieved in <hi>England, Scotland, Ireland:</hi> as ſcarce any <hi>Age</hi> can report the like: All theſe laid together, may cauſe us with aſtoniſhment to cry out, as it is in <hi>Balaams</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, <hi>What hath God wrought!</hi> Who can look upon<note place="margin">Num. 23. 23.</note> theſe things with an <hi>unprejudiced</hi> ſpirit, and not <hi>ſtand ſtill</hi> and <hi>wonder?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:40187:24"/>
               <p>And to <hi>you</hi> that are Saints <hi>experienced</hi> in the <hi>love</hi> of God, and the <hi>life</hi> of Chriſt, and the divine <hi>methods</hi> of grace, in your ſalvation; look hither, <hi>and wonder.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, wonder at that <hi>mercy</hi> that hath pardoned thee: conſidering what a kind of thing <hi>ſin</hi> is, how it ſtrikes at the very <hi>Authority, Dignity, Life,</hi> and <hi>Being</hi> of God: how it robs him of his glory, ſeeks to <hi>undermine</hi> him, in the great <hi>deſigns</hi> he is carrying on in the world, makes Him a <hi>ſhadow,</hi> a meer <hi>nothing,</hi> ſetting up <hi>it ſelf,</hi> or ſome <hi>poor</hi> creature in <hi>his</hi> Throne: I ſay, that God ſhould par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>ſuch a thing</hi> as this: yea, thouſand thouſands, even an <hi>infinite number</hi> of ſins, and that <hi>freely, above</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, and <hi>againſt</hi> the deſert of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſpeaks out</hi> his mercy <hi>wonderful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>wonder</hi> again at that <hi>grace</hi> which hath accepted thee, in thy <hi>rags;</hi> embraced thee, in thy <hi>blood;</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>after</hi> thee, when thou waſt running <hi>from it; laid hold</hi> on thee, and <hi>overcame</hi> thee, when thou waſt <hi>fighting</hi> againſt it.</p>
               <p>And ſo look upon his <hi>patience,</hi> and <hi>wonder at it,</hi> that did ſo long <hi>wait</hi> upon thee, bear and <hi>ſtrive</hi> with thee, whiles thou waſt deſperately <hi>fighting</hi> againſt heaven, and wilfully <hi>barring up</hi> thine heart againſt the <hi>moſt high.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then look upon that <hi>tranſcendent</hi> happineſs, thoſe unutterable <hi>delights, dignities, prerogatives</hi> and <hi>perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> which God hath provided <hi>for thee,</hi> and beſtowed upon <hi>thee</hi> in Jeſus Chriſt, look on them till thou art <hi>amazed</hi> before them.</p>
               <p>And further, look within thine <hi>own breaſt,</hi> and wonder at the <hi>goings</hi> and <hi>workings</hi> of God in thine <hi>own</hi> heart: what ſtrange <hi>innovations</hi> he hath made <hi>within thee:</hi> what glorious <hi>deliverances</hi> he hath accompliſht <hi>for thee:</hi> When Chriſt was upon the Earth, he <hi>opened</hi> the eys of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40187:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> the blind; <hi>unſtopped</hi> the ears of the <hi>deaf: raiſed</hi> the dead, <hi>diſpoſſeſſed</hi> the devils, <hi>rebuked</hi> the wind, <hi>calmed</hi> the ſeas, <hi>ſtopped</hi> iſſues of blood, <hi>cleanſed</hi> the Leapers, &amp;c. which the people beholding, in one place we read, <hi>they wondred greatly,</hi> in another, <hi>they were aſtoniſht with a great aſtoniſhment,</hi> in a third, ſaying, <hi>What manner of man is this?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So, canſt thou look within thee, and ſee all theſe works, and <hi>miracles</hi> wrought, in thine own heart? let that <hi>glorious</hi> power, that hath done <hi>theſe things,</hi> be <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful</hi> to thee.</p>
               <p>And from what I have now ſaid, there are three ſorts of perſons juſtly to be reproved.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Thoſe who in ſtead of wondring, do <hi>condemn</hi> and <hi>deride</hi> thoſe things that are <hi>wonderful,</hi> and which they cannot comprehend, as the <hi>Papiſts, Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, Arminians</hi> do the <hi>high</hi> and <hi>ſecret</hi> work of <hi>divine</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. Calv. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit lib. 3. ca.</hi> 23</note> Predeſtination; The <hi>Celeſtines,</hi> and <hi>Manichees</hi> the Doctrine of Gods particular Providence: And ſome in our days have exploded the deep <hi>myſtery</hi> of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> as a <hi>chaffy</hi> and <hi>abſurd</hi> Opinion: and ſo the <hi>high myſteries</hi> of the Goſpel, were laughed at, as ridiculous and <hi>fooliſh</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Melior eſt ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ignorantia quam temera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria ſcientia.</hi> Aug. de verb. Apoſt. Ser. 20.</note> things, when they were preached by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to the world; men meaſuring <hi>divine</hi> things by <hi>carnal</hi> reaſon, comprehend them not, and ſo <hi>turn</hi> from them, with offence or deriſion.</p>
               <p>Not but that all the <hi>truths</hi> of heaven, and all the wayes of <hi>Godlineſs</hi> are built upon the pureſt and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limeſt <hi>reaſon</hi> in the world: and when <hi>reaſon</hi> in man is <hi>elevated</hi> and <hi>renewed</hi> into its <hi>primitive</hi> ſtate, and is not <hi>byaſſed</hi> or ſeduced by fleſhly luſts, it ſuggeſts nothing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40187:25"/> that is <hi>repugnant</hi> to the <hi>Oracles</hi> of God, or inconſiſtent with true <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> but Reaſon conſidered as in its preſent <hi>ſituation</hi> in the midſt of <hi>fleſhly</hi> luſts, and <hi>debaſed</hi> and <hi>degraded</hi> by the Fall, ſo it <hi>diſcerns not the things of the Spirit, nor is it ſubject to the Law of God, neither indeed can be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, This ſerves alſo to reprove the <hi>Curious,</hi> who dive into things above their reach, and have an <hi>ear</hi> to hear where God hath not had a <hi>tongue</hi> to ſpeak, will venture to pry even into the <hi>ſecrets</hi> of heaven, and beat their brains about unattainable, if not unprofitable knowledge. Things <hi>above us,</hi> we are rather <hi>to admire,</hi> then too buſily inquire into: As <hi>Paul</hi> doth <hi>modeſtly leave</hi> that deep myſtery of the <hi>breaking off</hi> the Jews, and <hi>grafting in of</hi> the Gentiles with an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as we read, <hi>Rom. 11. 33. O the depth of the riches, of the wiſdom and knowledge of God!</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius Areop.</hi> reading the Book of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> left it thus, <hi>Non reprobo quod non intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go; ſed eò magis admiror, quo minus aſſequor; I do not reject what I do not underſtand; but the leſs I comprehend, the more I wonder.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here I might (though perhaps, not without a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle digreſſion) acquaint you with the frothy <hi>fancies,</hi> and vain <hi>diſquiſitions</hi> of ſome of the Schoolmen, and other <hi>modern</hi> Writers: As, <hi>One will undertake to tell us what was our Saviours diſpute among the Doctors: Another, what he wrote with his finger upon the ground: a third, what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came of</hi> Moſes <hi>his body; and where is locall hell; and what language Saints ſhall ſpeak in heaven; and who ſhall ſit high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in heaven; and when is the day of Judgement; and in what place the world ſhall be judged.</hi> When <hi>Peter</hi> asked our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſomewhat <hi>a curious queſtion</hi> concerning <hi>John, Joh. 21. 21. And what ſhall this man do?</hi> Chriſts takes
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40187:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> him up ſomewhat <hi>roundly,</hi> in the next verſe, <hi>If I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee? follow thou me;</hi> And ſo the <hi>diſciples</hi> propounding a queſtion of the like <hi>import,</hi> Act. 1. 6. <hi>Lord, wilt thou at this time reſtore again the Kingdom to Iſrael; Jeſus Chriſt</hi> gives them a <hi>check</hi> for it, in the following words. <hi>It is not for you to know the times and ſeaſons which the Father hath put in his own power;</hi> ſo far as we can find <hi>footing,</hi> it is ſafe to <hi>wade;</hi> and ſo far as is <hi>revealed,</hi> to ſearch, and leave <hi>ſecret things</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him to whom they do properly belong.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, and <hi>eſpecially,</hi> This reproves <hi>ſottiſh people</hi> among us, who though the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> is thus <hi>every way</hi> wonderful, in his <hi>Perſon, Offices,</hi> and <hi>Works;</hi> and though God hath in ſuch an admirable way <hi>diſcovered</hi> himſelf, through him, unto the world; yet <hi>paſs him by, look not</hi> upon him, as if there was <hi>nothing</hi> in him <hi>worthy</hi> their thoughts, or to be <hi>wondred</hi> at.</p>
               <p>Some are <hi>Ignorant</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, have never <hi>ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly</hi> ſet themſelves to inquire into the <hi>deep myſteries</hi> of the Goſpel, <hi>in whom the god of this world hath blinded</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>their eyes, that the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt ſhines not upon them,</hi> but live as if there was neither <hi>Chriſt,</hi> nor <hi>Goſpel,</hi> nor <hi>Heaven,</hi> nor <hi>God</hi> in the world. And though he hath made <hi>his arm</hi> ſo naked, in his <hi>might works</hi> among us; yet have not ſeen him, or taken notice of him to this day. <hi>David</hi> ſadly complains in <hi>Pſal. 106. 7. Our Fathers underſtood not thy wonders in Eggpt, &amp;c. but provoked thee at the ſea, even the red ſea:</hi> ſo, many <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not</hi> the preſent <hi>deſign</hi> of God, and the <hi>import</hi> of his <hi>late glorious</hi> works; but by their <hi>murmurings, diſcontents,</hi> and <hi>detractions</hi> from his glory, provoke him to <hi>anger</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
               <p>Others are taken up about things <hi>ſecular</hi> and <hi>earthly;</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:40187:26"/> about their <hi>private</hi> ends, <hi>perſonal</hi> intereſts, <hi>raiſing</hi> their eſtates, <hi>advancing</hi> themſelves, and their children, and are ſo <hi>buried</hi> in the world, that they look not up to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, to admire thoſe <hi>divine wonders</hi> that are <hi>evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently</hi> held forth in him. The Prophet complains of ſome, <hi>Iſa. 5. 12. That the Harp the Viol, the Tabret, and wine are in their Feaſts, but they regard not the works of the Lord, nor conſider the operation of his hands.</hi> Men, whoſe eyes are <hi>bewitched</hi> and <hi>dazzeled</hi> with the <hi>inchanting ſplendor</hi> of earthly things, are <hi>diſabled</hi> from beholding and admiring the <hi>Spiritual</hi> glory of Jeſus Chriſt, and of <hi>his</hi> works. <hi>Philo Judaeus,</hi> ſpeaking of ſuch perſons, gives them this<note place="margin">Lib. de mundi opificio.</note> 
                  <hi>Character,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>more admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the world, then the maker of the world.</hi> God hath made the <hi>creatures,</hi> and all the beauties and delights of them to be as ſo many <hi>ſteps</hi> to raiſe men <hi>up</hi> to himſelf, and they <hi>determine</hi> their thoughts and affections <hi>upon them,</hi> and riſe no higher, and ſo are ſpiritually <hi>guilty</hi> of that <hi>Idolatry</hi> which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> chargeth upon the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, <hi>Rom. 1. Who worſhipped, and ſerved the creature more then the Creator, God bleſſed for ever.</hi> Rom. 1. 25.</p>
               <p>But that we may now in the cloſe of all excite you to this <hi>heavenly work</hi> of Admiration, we ſhall ſet it before you, both in the <hi>ſublimity,</hi> and the <hi>efficacy</hi> of it, that you may not look upon it as a <hi>fancy,</hi> or a meer <hi>ſpeculation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, for the <hi>ſublimity</hi> of it: This <hi>divine admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is that <hi>act</hi> of the ſoul, which <hi>of all others</hi> doth <hi>moſt</hi> ſublimate and raiſe it. It is a kind of <hi>divine rapture,</hi> wherein the ſoul is brought to <hi>ſee that</hi> which is <hi>infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely</hi> above all ſight, and to <hi>enjoy</hi> that which is beyond all <hi>comprehenſion:</hi> The ſoul hath <hi>never</hi> ſuch a clear ſight of God <hi>as God,</hi> then when ſhe is <hi>rapt up</hi> higheſt, in the <hi>admiration</hi> of him: for ſo long as in our <hi>purſuits</hi> after
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40187:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> God in his being, or in his works, we <hi>comprehend</hi> what we purſue, we conceive <hi>him</hi> under <hi>ſome finite notion,</hi> and make but a <hi>creature</hi> of him; but, when the ſoul <hi>loſeth</hi> it ſelf in him, when all underſtanding <hi>ceaſeth;</hi> and is ſilently <hi>wondring</hi> at what it <hi>cannot</hi> comprehend, and lies down <hi>aſtoniſht</hi> under the <hi>brightneſs</hi> of that glory it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>behold:</hi> now hath it a <hi>rude</hi> diſcovery, even of <hi>infinity,</hi> and <hi>incomprehenſibleneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus the <hi>Saints</hi> in glory, though their ſpirits are <hi>raiſed, enlarged, fortified,</hi> that they might be <hi>able</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>living ſtreams</hi> of bliſs, pleaſures, and beauty that flow from the <hi>face</hi> of God; <hi>yet,</hi> there is <hi>ſomething</hi> ſtill in <hi>him</hi> infinitely <hi>beyond</hi> what they receive, or <hi>can poſsibly</hi> comprehend, into which they are <hi>abſorpt,</hi> and <hi>ſwallowed up,</hi> and enjoy it only by a holy <hi>amazement,</hi> and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But Secondly, look upon it in the <hi>efficacy</hi> of it, this admiring Jeſus Chriſt, will,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Enlarge, and <hi>open our mouths</hi> in his praiſes. How natural is it for <hi>greatneſs</hi> and <hi>admired</hi> excellency, to ſet the heart and tongue upon praiſing! <hi>Out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh:</hi> If the heart be filled with <hi>anger,</hi> the tongue will be <hi>bitter</hi> and invective: If with <hi>joy,</hi> it is full of ſinging and <hi>triumphant</hi> expreſſions of its own <hi>contentment:</hi> and ſo, if it be filled with <hi>admiration</hi> of any excellency, though for a while it may be ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, yet will <hi>preſently</hi> break forth into exaltation and praiſe. It is ſaid, <hi>Matth. 15. 31. When the multitude heard the dumb to ſpeak, and ſaw the lame to walk, they wondred, and glorified God;</hi> firſt; <hi>wondred,</hi> and then <hi>glorified.</hi> And ſo 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 10. It is ſaid, <hi>Chriſt ſhall come to be admired in his Saints, and to be glorified in them that believe.</hi> We cannot but <hi>glorifie</hi> him, when once we do <hi>admire</hi> him.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40187:27"/> And indeed, what is not <hi>wonderful</hi> to us, that we are not apt much to extoll or praiſe. As I have read of a <hi>fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,</hi> who having peruſed a very <hi>obſcure</hi> and difficult <hi>Author,</hi> and being demanded his judgement of it, Anſwered, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>What I underſtood in him was excellent, and what I underſtood not, ſure was more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent;</hi> ſo will <hi>the ſoul</hi> that hath a <hi>real</hi> acquaintance with Jeſus Chriſt ſay: what I know and underſtand of him <hi>is very ſweet, glorious,</hi> and worthy of <hi>praiſe:</hi> but, what I cannot underſtand, but <hi>is yet</hi> above my reach, that is ſure <hi>more ſweet,</hi> more <hi>glorious,</hi> and more <hi>praiſe worthy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. This will alſo <hi>poſſeſs</hi> the ſoul with an <hi>awful,</hi> and <hi>reverential</hi> fear of him: A <hi>divine</hi> and <hi>holy</hi> fear of God, <hi>fills</hi> the heart, whiles it is <hi>wondring at him.</hi> When the ſoul is <hi>gazing</hi> upon a <hi>majeſty</hi> and <hi>glory,</hi> that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely above it, it cannot but ſecretly <hi>tremble</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it. As the Diſciples beholding the glory of Chriſt, at his <hi>Transfiguration,</hi> Matth. 17. <hi>it is ſaid, they fell on their faces, and were ſore afraid.</hi> And <hi>Job</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving looked upon, and wondred at the <hi>incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible</hi> works of God, confeſſeth, <hi>Chap. 37. 1. That his heart trembled, and was moved out of its place.</hi> Therefore well have the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> made <hi>admiration</hi> one of the kinds of fear; for the ſoul hath a ſecret fear of the <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of that object, which it <hi>wonders</hi> at, but cannot <hi>comprehend:</hi> As <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaking of the <hi>deeps</hi> of divine<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. de verb. Apoſt. Serm.</hi> 20.</note> Providence, and the <hi>ſecrets</hi> of Predeſtination, againſt thoſe that cavil at them, ſaith, <hi>Quaeris turationem? ego ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paveſcam altitudinem: Art thou enquiring a reaſon? I will tremble at the heighth, &amp;c.</hi> When a man is beholding the infinite <hi>wiſdom, purity,</hi> and <hi>excellency</hi> of Chriſt, it cannot but make him to <hi>reflect</hi> upon his own <hi>darkneſs, filthineſs,</hi> and <hi>baſeneſs,</hi> with an <hi>holy</hi> fear and trembling.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:40187:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>3. This will alſo draw out the ſoul to a more <hi>confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent dependance</hi> upon Jeſus Chriſt. Could we compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the <hi>utmoſt bounds</hi> of that power and wiſdom, that righteouſneſs and fulneſs that is in him: they were but <hi>finite,</hi> and ſo we might diſtruſt them, as not able to <hi>ſerve</hi> our turns: But ſeeing he is <hi>every way wonderful,</hi> his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs a <hi>wonderful</hi> righteouſneſs, his <hi>power, wiſdom, mercy,</hi> all <hi>wonderful,</hi> above all our thoughts: this makes <hi>him</hi> to be a <hi>ſure</hi> Bulwark, a <hi>ſtrong</hi> and <hi>everlaſting</hi> Rock for the ſoul to reſt and betruſt it ſelf upon. So that, haſt thou been a <hi>wonderful</hi> ſinner? here is <hi>a more wonderful Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour:</hi> are thy ſins <hi>wonderfully</hi> great? here is <hi>a more won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful mercy</hi> to <hi>pardon</hi> them, and <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> to <hi>attone</hi> for them: And are thy wants, thy weakneſs, thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers <hi>wonderful,</hi> that thou canſt not <hi>know</hi> them? here is power, holineſs, fulneſs more <hi>wonderful,</hi> and farther <hi>above</hi> thy knowledge. And therefore caſt thy ſelf with much confidence upon him in all ſtreights, wants, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and difficulties whatſoever.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This will alſo have another effect, it will <hi>take off thine heart</hi> from admiring the creature. By thy <hi>wondring</hi> at Jeſus Chriſt, thy ſoul will be ſo <hi>raiſed</hi> and <hi>enlarged,</hi> that it will apprehend <hi>all things</hi> beſides him, but mean and trivial. The <hi>Eye,</hi> having beheld the brightneſs of the <hi>Sun,</hi> ſeeth all other light <hi>far below it. Moſes</hi> ſeeing him that is <hi>Inviſible,</hi> beheld ſuch <hi>riches</hi> and <hi>glory,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed ſuch <hi>ſweetneſs</hi> and pleaſures in God, as made the<note place="margin">Heb. 11. 24. 25. 29.</note> glory and pleaſures of <hi>Pharoahs Court</hi> mean, and worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in his eſteem. <hi>Paul</hi> being <hi>rapt up to the third heavens,</hi> and in a divine <hi>extaſie,</hi> admiring the <hi>unutterable things</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 8.</note> of Chriſt, accounted <hi>all</hi> but <hi>loſs and dung</hi> for the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him. And our <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> living alwaies in the clear ſight of his Fathers glory, was not at all <hi>allured</hi> or
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40187:28"/> 
                  <hi>affected</hi> with the glory of the <hi>Kingdoms of this world,</hi> when it was by Satan ſet before him. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaith the Philoſopher, <hi>Men of great and raiſed ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, deſpiſe thoſe things which others are taken with.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, nothing will be ſo effectual to <hi>bring down</hi> the thoughts of man to a mean eſteem of himſelf, then to be <hi>thus</hi> raiſed in the <hi>admiration</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt. That <hi>act</hi> of the ſoul that doth <hi>moſt</hi> exalt Chriſt, doth <hi>moſt</hi> debaſe man. As thoſe two Stars called <hi>Gemini,</hi> the one <hi>ariſeth</hi> as the other <hi>falleth:</hi> So as Chriſt is <hi>raiſed</hi> and exalted <hi>in us,</hi> ſo do <hi>we</hi> fall down <hi>lower</hi> and <hi>lower</hi> in the eſteem of our ſelves.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Laſtly, This will alſo <hi>lead</hi> the heart into an <hi>holy boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and <hi>triumphant rejoycing</hi> in Jeſus Chriſt. As man will more boaſt in a <hi>treaſure</hi> that he knows is <hi>inexhauſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> then in the greateſt riches and poſſeſſions that he can diſcover the <hi>bounds</hi> of; So whiles we are <hi>beholding</hi> the fulneſs and riches of Chriſt, as <hi>inexhauſted,</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable,</hi> and are <hi>wondring</hi> at them; this will <hi>naturally</hi> carry out our ſpirits to <hi>boaſt</hi> and <hi>triumph</hi> in him; When <hi>after all</hi> thy knowledge of him, thy <hi>Commmnion</hi> with him, thy <hi>enjoyments</hi> and <hi>receits</hi> from him, thou heareſt <hi>yet a voice</hi> ſpeaking to thee, thou ſhalt <hi>yet</hi> enjoy and <hi>ſee greater things then theſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> laſt: I have only one word more to add: If Jeſus Chriſt be thus <hi>wonderful,</hi> and declares <hi>this name of his,</hi> eſpecially in our ſalvation: Let us learn and endeavor to be <hi>wonderful</hi> in <hi>our</hi> actings <hi>for him,</hi> as he is in his actings <hi>for us.</hi> That we may now all <hi>ſtrive</hi> to be (as it was ſaid of<note place="margin">Zach. 3. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Joſhua</hi> the Prieſt, and his fellows in another ſenſe) <hi>men of wonder.</hi> Surely if we do viſibly <hi>deny our ſelves,</hi> ſubject all our own <hi>Intereſts</hi> to the <hi>glory</hi> of Chriſt, the promoting the Goſpel, and <hi>eſtabliſhing</hi> Juſtice and Righteouſneſs <hi>in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40187:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Nation,</hi> and in our whole converſation, <hi>croſs</hi> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon courſe of the world, we ſhall be <hi>men of wonder</hi> in our generation, and in <hi>generations</hi> yet to come: that <hi>England</hi> may be made the <hi>wonder of the world</hi> for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, wiſdom, truth, and holineſs, as it hath been made the <hi>wonder of the world</hi> for ſalvations and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances. Surely we ſhall not anſwer the <hi>extraordinary</hi> appearances of Chriſt <hi>for us,</hi> if we do not now <hi>extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily</hi> and eminently <hi>appear</hi> for him: He now hath put us to the <hi>tryal,</hi> by giving <hi>great opportunities</hi> into our hands; and certainly great things may be done, if we lay down <hi>Animoſities, ſelf-ends,</hi> and <hi>corrupt</hi> principles, and with <hi>ſincerity, wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>unity,</hi> addreſs to the <hi>great works</hi> of God and <hi>the Nation</hi> that are before us. The change of <hi>Government</hi> will avail us little; the name of a <hi>Commonwealth</hi> will do little ſervice, if we do not ſee the <hi>common good</hi> ſought and promoted, <hi>common grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> and <hi>burthens removed,</hi> and <hi>Common Juſtice</hi> impartially <hi>adminiſtred</hi> throughout the Nation. And O that you (Right Hnorable) who ſit at the <hi>Stern</hi> of this City, and thoſe that <hi>do,</hi> or hereafter <hi>may ſit</hi> at the Stern of this <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> would ſet their ſhoulders <hi>effectually</hi> to theſe great works, that the <hi>poor Church</hi> of Chriſt may <hi>live</hi> and <hi>flouriſh</hi> under the wings of ſuch Rulers and Governors, which the <hi>Lord</hi> hath promiſed ſhe ſhould <hi>enjoy</hi> in theſe <hi>laſt times:</hi> And that ſweet promiſe may be fulfilled upon <hi>her, Iſai. 60. 17, 18. I will alſo make thy Officers peace, and thine Exactors Righteouſneſs; Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence ſhall no more be heard in thy Land, waſting nor deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction within thy borders; but thou ſhalt call thy wals Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and thy gates Praiſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
